{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which Sultan of Delhi was the first to charge GHARI or HOUSE TAX?\n",
            "optionA": "  Balban ",
            "optionB": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionC": "  Mohammad bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Firoz Shah Tughlaq ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlauddin Khalji was the First Sultan of Delhi to charge Ghari or House Tax. ",
            "keyString": "488644s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the quit India movement launched?",
            "optionA": "  1930 ",
            "optionB": "  1940 ",
            "optionC": "  1942 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quit India Movement, or the August Movement, was a movement launched at the Bombay session of the All-India Congress Committee by Gandhiji on 8 August 1942, during World War II, demanding an end to British Rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "488690s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Viceroy of India had largest tenure during British rule:",
            "optionA": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Bentick ",
            "optionD": "  None of above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor General and Viceroy of India (1936-1944) Lord Linlithgow was Viceroy of India from 1936 to 1944 and this eight years period was longest reign as Viceroy of India. ",
            "keyString": "488704s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was governor general when the 1857 revolt broke out?\n ",
            "optionA": "  Canning ",
            "optionB": "  Lawrence ",
            "optionC": "  Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharles Canning, the Governor-General of India during the rebellion when the 1857 revolt broke out. ",
            "keyString": "488716s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The title VIKRAMADITYA was assumed by: ",
            "optionA": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta II ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Vikramaditya\" was a common title adopted by several Indian kings, and the Vikramaditya legends may be embellished accounts of different kings (particularly Chandragupta II). ",
            "keyString": "488728s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said, \u201cthis (the revolt 1857) was an eruption of social volcano, where many spent forces found vent. After the eruption, the whole social topography had changed; the scars if rebellion remained deep and shining?\u201d",
            "optionA": "  J K Hikki ",
            "optionB": "  Ashok Mehta ",
            "optionC": "  K M Pannikar ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshok Mehta said, \u201cthis (the revolt 1857) was an eruption of social volcano, where many spent forces found vent. After the eruption, the whole social topography had changed; the scars if rebellion remained deep and shining\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "653960s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sisir Kumar Ghosh, Shambhuchand Mukherhee, Kali Mohan Das and Jogesh Chandra Dutt were editors of:",
            "optionA": "  Amrit Bazar Patrika ",
            "optionB": "  Hindu ",
            "optionC": "  Sudharak ",
            "optionD": "  Yugantar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSisir Kumar Ghosh, Shambhuchand Mukherjee, Kali Mohan Das and Jogesh Chandra Dutt were editors of \u2013 Amrit Bazar Patrika. ",
            "keyString": "659123s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the British Acts provided for the establishment of All India Federation at the centre ?",
            "optionA": "  The Government of India Act 1935. ",
            "optionB": "  The Government of India Act 1919. ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Independence act 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  The Registration act, 1908 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act, 1935 provided for the establishment of Federal Court to interpret the Act and adjudicate disputes relating to the federal matters. It provided that the Federal Courts should consist of one Chief justice and not more than six judges. ",
            "keyString": "659187s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cabinet mission arrived in Delhi on:",
            "optionA": "  August 24, 1946 ",
            "optionB": "  May 24, 1946 ",
            "optionC": "  March 24, 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  April 24, 1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Mission of 1946 came to India aimed to discuss the transfer of power from the British government to the Indian leadership, with the aim of preserving India's unity and granting it independence. He came of March 24, 1946. ",
            "keyString": "659677s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British government declared Communist Party of India illegal in:\t\n",
            "optionA": "  1924 ",
            "optionB": "  1934 ",
            "optionC": "  1930 ",
            "optionD": "  1939 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British government, did not favour the activities of the Communists in India and on 23rd July, 1934 it imposed a ban on the functioning of the party. ",
            "keyString": "660077s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pioneer of Indian communism was",
            "optionA": "  M.N. Roy ",
            "optionB": "  G.N Ganguly ",
            "optionC": "  P.C Chandra ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManabendra Nath Roy (21 March 1887 \u2013 26 January 1954), born Narendra Nath Bhattacharya, was an Indian revolutionary, radical activist and political theorist, as well as a noted philosopher in the 20th century. Roy was a founder of the Mexican Communist Party and the Communist Party of India. He was the pioneer of Indian communism. ",
            "keyString": "801619s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom did B.G.Tilak call the \"Diamond of India\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale. ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tB.G.Tilak called the \"Diamond of India\" to Gopal Krishna Gokhale. ",
            "keyString": "804087s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Plassey was fought in",
            "optionA": "  1757 ",
            "optionB": "  1782 ",
            "optionC": "  1748 ",
            "optionD": "  1764 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 23 June 1757, the Battle of Plassey was fought between the forces of Siraj Ud Daulah, and his French support troops and the troops of the British East India Company, led by Robert Clive. This event was a part of the Seven Years War. ",
            "keyString": "804574s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The territory of Porus who offered strong resistance to Alexander was situated between the rivers of",
            "optionA": "  Sutlej and Beas ",
            "optionB": "  Jhelum and Chenab ",
            "optionC": "  Ravi and Chenab ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga and Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe territory of Porus who offered strong resistance to Alexander was situated between the rivers of Jhelum and Chenab.",
            "keyString": "804860s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under Akbar, the Mir Bakshi was required to look after",
            "optionA": "  military affairs ",
            "optionB": "  the state treasury ",
            "optionC": "  the royal household ",
            "optionD": "  the land revenue system ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head of the military was called the Mir Bakshi, appointed from among the leading nobles of the court. The Mir Bakshi was in charge of intelligence gathering, and also made recommendations to the emperor for military appointments and promotions. ",
            "keyString": "805115s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1821 Raja Ram Mohan Roy started the Bengal quarterly:",
            "optionA": "  Samvad Kaumudi ",
            "optionB": "  Bengali renaissance ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal Gazette ",
            "optionD": "  The Brahmonical ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1821 Raja Ram Mohan Roy started the Bengal quarterly Samvad Kaumudi. ",
            "keyString": "906859s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first man after the revolt of 1857 who wanted to overthrow the British regime by means of an armed rebellion and establish self-government in India was:",
            "optionA": "  Bhakt Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Nana Sahib ",
            "optionC": "  Vasudeo Balwant Phadke ",
            "optionD": "  Jung Bhadur Rana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first man after the revolt of 1857 who wanted to overthrow the British regime by means of an armed rebellion and establish self-government in India was Vasudeo Balwant Phadke. ",
            "keyString": "907141s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established East India Association in London 1866?",
            "optionA": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai  Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  V. O. Chidambaram Pillai ",
            "optionD": "  Hemu Kalani ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Association was founded by Dadabhai Naoroji in 1866, in collaboration with Indians and retired British officials in London. ",
            "keyString": "907399s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1893 Mahatma Gandhi went to South Africa in connection with the trial of a merchant:",
            "optionA": "  Hemu Kalani ",
            "optionB": "  Sachindra Bakshi ",
            "optionC": "  Manmath Nath Gupta ",
            "optionD": "  Abdulla Seth ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was a long journey from India to South Africa. Gandhi reached the port of Natal towards the end of May, 1893. The first thing he noticed was that the Indians there were treated with little respect. Within a week of his arrival in Durban, he visited the court with Abdulla Seth of Dada, Abdulla &Co. ",
            "keyString": "907698s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which foreigner arrived in India on Nov. 16, 1893?\n",
            "optionA": "  Khan Abdul Gaffar ",
            "optionB": "  W A Hume ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant arrived in India on Nov. 16, 1893. ",
            "keyString": "907949s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which act of British India, was the Governor General empowered to issue ordinance ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Indian Councils Act, 1861 ",
            "optionB": "  Charter Act of 1853 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act, 1858 ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Council Act, 1892 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Councils Act 1861. An Act to make better Provision for the Constitution of the Council of the Governor General of India, and for the Local Government of the several Presidencies and Provinces of India, and for the temporary Government of India in the event of a Vacancy in the Office of Governor General. ",
            "keyString": "987143s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1915-16 the Home Rule League movement was launched under the leadership of : \n",
            "optionA": "  Mohammad Ali Jinnah and G. S. Khaparde ",
            "optionB": "  G. S. Khaparde and Sir S. Subramania Iyer ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant and Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Sir S. Subramania Iyer and Mohammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant started the Home Rule League in September, 1916, and Tilak started it in April 1916. Tilak\u2019s movement was confined to Maharashtra and Karnataka. And Annie Besant movement spread to other parts of India. ",
            "keyString": "988344s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1932, Poona Pact was signed between:\n",
            "optionA": "  Gandhiji and Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhiji and Dr. ",
            "optionC": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Poona Pact refers to an agreement between B. R. Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi on the reservation of electoral seats for the depressed classes in the legislature of British India government. It was made on 24 September 1932 at Yerwada Central Jail in Poona, India and was signed by Mahatma Gandhi, B.R Ambedkar and some other leaders as a means to end the fast that Gandhi was undertaking in jail as a protest against the decision by British prime minister Ramsay MacDonald to give separate electorates to depressed classes for the election of members of provincial legislative assemblies in British India. They finally agreed upon 148 electoral seats. ",
            "keyString": "988995s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Dyarchy was started by :\n",
            "optionA": "  Indian Council Act, 1861 ",
            "optionB": "  Minto-Morley Reforms, 1909 ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Council Act, 1992 ",
            "optionD": "  Montague-Chelmsford Reforms, 1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India act 1919 was passed on the basis of recommendations of Lord Chelmsford and Samuel Montagu to introduce self-governing institutions gradually to India. This act covered 10 years from 1919 to 1929. ",
            "keyString": "989463s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which movement was started by Mahatma Gandhi on March 12, 1930?\n",
            "optionA": "  Khilafat movement ",
            "optionB": "  Noncooperation Co-operation ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Quit India Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn March 12, 1930, Indian independence leader Mohandas Gandhi begins a defiant march to the sea in protest of the British monopoly on salt, his boldest act of civil disobedience yet against British rule in India.",
            "keyString": "989929s50m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term samanta, meaning a feudatory from the sixth century AD, originally meant  a",
            "optionA": "  slave ",
            "optionB": "  cultivator ",
            "optionC": "  neighbour ",
            "optionD": "  foreigner ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term samanta, meaning a feudatory from the sixth century AD, originally meant a Neighbour. ",
            "keyString": "74844s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To evolve a peaceful settlement of the conflict between India and China, which of the following non-aligned Afro-Asian nations participated in a conference held in December 1962?",
            "optionA": "  Burma (now Myanmar), Combodia, Indonesia and UAR ",
            "optionB": "  Burma, Sri Lanka, Combodia and Indonesia ",
            "optionC": "  Burma, Indonesia, Ghana and Sri Lanka ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBurma (now Myanmar), Combodia, Indonesia, UAR, Sri Lanka, and Ghana, all the countries which are mentioned here have participated in the conference held in December 1962. ",
            "keyString": "75353s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The text of the document called Mahzar, by which Akbar assumed the role of supreme arbiter in the matters of religion is found in",
            "optionA": "  Nizamuddin's Tabaqat-I-Akbari ",
            "optionB": "  Arif Quandahari's Tarikh-I-Alfi ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Fazl's Akbarnama ",
            "optionD": "  Badauni's Muntakahab-ut-Tawarikh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Akbarnama which translates to Book of Akbar, is the official chronicle of the reign of Akbar, the third Mughal Emperor, commissioned by Akbar himself by his court historian and biographer, Abul-Fazl ibn Mubarak who was one of the nine jewels in Akbar's court. The text of the document called Mahzar, by which Akbar assumed the role of supreme arbiter in the matters of religion is found in it. ",
            "keyString": "75382s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tulsidas, the author of Ramcharitmanas, was a contemporary of which of the following rulers?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Sher Shah Suri ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTulsidas wrote several popular works in Sanskrit and Awadhi; he is best known as the author of the epic Ramcharitmanas, a retelling of the Sanskrit Ramayana based on Rama's life in the vernacular Awadhi dialect of Hindi. He was a contemporary of Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "75581s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To meet the educational needs of the people, the Madarasa-I-Nasiri was built in the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Qutub-ud-din Aibak ",
            "optionB": "  Iltutmish ",
            "optionC": "  Ruknuddin Firoz Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Jalal-id-din Khilji ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo meet the educational needs of the people, the Madarasa-I Nasiri was built in the reign of Iltutmish. ",
            "keyString": "75766s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar organized a Bhishkrit Hitkari Sabha, (The Depressed Classes Institute) in :",
            "optionA": "  1924 ",
            "optionB": "  1920 ",
            "optionC": "  1916 ",
            "optionD": "  1911 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. B. R. Ambedkar organized a Bhishkrit Hitkari Sabha, (The Depressed Classes Institute) in 1924. ",
            "keyString": "175509s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Gandhi-Irwin Pact was signed on :",
            "optionA": "  July 5, 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  June 5, 1931 ",
            "optionC": "  March 5, 1931 ",
            "optionD": "  January 5, 1931 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhi-Irwin Pact was a political agreement signed by Mahatma Gandhi and Lord Irwin, the then Viceroy of India, on 5 March 1931 before the second Round Table Conference in London. ",
            "keyString": "175571s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In July 1933 the Congress decided to launch:",
            "optionA": "  An Individual Civil Disobedience ",
            "optionB": "  Satyagrah ",
            "optionC": "  Bharat Chhoro Aandolan  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi arrived from London on 28 December 1931 and on that day, Congress Working Committee decided to resume the Civil Disobedience Movement. Within a week, on 4 January 1932, Gandhi was arrested. Officially, the Civil Disobedience movement was suspended in May 1933 and it was finally withdrawn in May 1934. ",
            "keyString": "176057s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \u201cEvery blow on my body will prove a nail in the coffin of the British Empire\u201d?\n",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Kunwar Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Chandra Sekhar Azaad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Lajpat Rai said \u201cEvery blow on my body will prove a nail in the coffin of the British Empire\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "177300s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In March 1923 Chittranjan Das along with Motilal Nehru formed : ",
            "optionA": "  The Gaddar Party ",
            "optionB": "  The Forward Block ",
            "optionC": "  The Swaraj Party ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Swaraj Party as established as the Congress-Khilafat Swaraj Party. It was a political party formed in India in January 1923 after the Gaya annual conference in December 1922 of the National Congress, that sought greater self-government and political freedom for the Indian people from the British Raj. It was inspired by the concept of Swaraj. In Hindi and many other languages of India, swaraj means \"independence\" or \"self-rule.\" The two most important leaders were Chittaranjan Das, who was its president and Motilal Nehru, who was its secretary. ",
            "keyString": "182034s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In order to study the position of education Indian constitutional commission was constituted in 1929 under the chairmanship of",
            "optionA": "  Phillip Uartog ",
            "optionB": "  Phillip Reading ",
            "optionC": "  Uartog Reading ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn order to study the position of education Indian constitutional commission was constituted in 1929 under the chairmanship of Phillip Uartog. ",
            "keyString": "276022s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said - \u201cpatriotism is religion and religion is love for India?\u201d",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Ashok Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  Bankim Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was uttered by Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay or Bankim Chandra Chatterjee. He was the first to initiate the slogan \"Vande Mataram\". ",
            "keyString": "276340s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The congress policy of prayer and petition ultimately came to an end under the guidance of",
            "optionA": "  B G Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak described the method of three P's \u2013 Prayer, petition and protest as political mendicancy. ",
            "keyString": "277026s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\u201cIn this instance we could not play off the Mohammedans against the Hindus.\u201d To which one of the following events did this remark of Aitchison relate?",
            "optionA": "  Bang Bhang ",
            "optionB": "  Santhal Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Kishan Andolan ",
            "optionD": "  Revolt of 1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u201cIn this instance we could not play off the Mohammedans against the Hindus.\u201d This remark of Aitchison relate to Revolt of 1857. ",
            "keyString": "277290s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "While delivering the presidential address\u2019 The Congress president who advocated the introduction of Roman Script for Hindi language was",
            "optionA": "  Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Sankaran Nair ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Haripura session of 1938, the Congress President Subhash Chandra Bose advocated the introduction of Roman script for Hindi language. ",
            "keyString": "277540s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Universities in the Presidency towns in India were established in",
            "optionA": "  1857 ",
            "optionB": "  1858 ",
            "optionC": "  1900 ",
            "optionD": "  1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUniversities in the Presidency towns in India were established in 1857. ",
            "keyString": "380142s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vijayanagara king who employed skilled archers of the Turkish clan and raised the fighting capacity of his bowmen was",
            "optionA": "  Bukka I ",
            "optionB": "  Devaraya I ",
            "optionC": "  Krishnadevaraya ",
            "optionD": "  Ramaraya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSrikrishna devaraya is the king who employed skilled arches of the Turkish clan and raised the fighting capacity of his bowmen",
            "keyString": "382761s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Guptas in eastern India, there was probably an intermediate level of administration between visayas (districts) and villages. Identify it.",
            "optionA": "  Bhukit ",
            "optionB": "  Pradesa ",
            "optionC": "  Vithi ",
            "optionD": "  Ahara ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Guptas in eastern India, there was probably an intermediate level of administration between vishayas (districts) and villages (Vithi). ",
            "keyString": "383617s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The two principles monuments of Alaud-din Khilji's reign - the Jama  Masjid at Kana and Alai Darwaza - were constructed at",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Dhar ",
            "optionD": "  Gulbarga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe two principles monuments of Alaud-din Khilji's reign - the Jama at Kana Masjid and Alai Darwaza - were constructed at Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "384558s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term Nirgrantha is associated with",
            "optionA": "  Ajivikas ",
            "optionB": "  Charvakas ",
            "optionC": "  Jains ",
            "optionD": "  Pasupatas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Nirgrantha is a term that specifically refers to Jains in religious and philosophical works from the Indian religions. ",
            "keyString": "384723s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded Anushulin Samiti in 1907 in Dhaka?\n",
            "optionA": "  Shambhuchand Mukherjee ",
            "optionB": "  Kali Mohan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Barindra Ghosh and Bhupendra Nath Dutt ",
            "optionD": "  Jogesh Chandra Dutt E.  Pulin Behari Das ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDhaka Anushilan Samiti was a branch of the Anushilan Samiti founded in the city of Dhaka in November 1905. Initially a group of eighty under the leadership of Pulin Behari Das, it \"spread like wildfire\" throughout the province of East Bengal. More than 500 branches were opened, linked by a \"close and detailed organization\" to Palin's headquarters at Dhaka. It absorbed smaller groups in the province and soon overshadowed its parent organization in Calcutta. Source :wikipedia.org ",
            "keyString": "473245s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sarojini Naidu was elected Congress President at : ",
            "optionA": "  Haripura, 1938 ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay, 1934 ",
            "optionC": "  Madras Session, 1927 ",
            "optionD": "  Kanpur Session ,1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1925, Naidu presided over the annual session of Indian National Congress at Cawnpore (now Kanpur). In 1929, she presided over East African Indian Congress in South Africa. She was awarded the Kaisar-i-Hind Medal by the British government for her work during the plague epidemic in India. ",
            "keyString": "473317s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1918 who founded Ahmedabad Textile Labour Association ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Mohammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the year 1918 father of the nation Mahatma Gandhi along with Anasuya Sarabhai and Shankerlal Banker founded the Ahmadabad textile labour association. ",
            "keyString": "473808s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1942, British Prime Minister Winston Churchill sent :\n",
            "optionA": "  Wavell Mission to India ",
            "optionB": "  Cripps Mission to India ",
            "optionC": "  Mount  Mission to India ",
            "optionD": "  August Offer  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 11 March 1942, Prime Minister Winston Churchill announced that Sir Stafford Cripps, a member of the British Cabinet, would be sent to India from 22 March to 11 April to work out a formula for India\u2019s participation in the war and partial transfer of power acceptable to all three, the Hindu and Muslim parties in India as well as the British forces. His negotiating mandate was the \u201cDraft Declaration\u201d, a document on which the War Cabinet had agreed after along discussion laying out a middle ground acceptable to the British, including self-government after the war. ",
            "keyString": "474884s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The demand officially made by the Congress for a Constituent Assembly to frame the Constitution of India was accepted in principal by the British government in what is known as : \n",
            "optionA": "  Cripps Mission 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India, 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  Independent India 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  August Offer of 1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAugust Offer of 1940. Roy, a pioneer of the Communist movement in India and an advocate of radical democracy. It became an official demand of the Indian National Congress in 1935, C. Rajagopalachari voiced the demand for a Constituent Assembly on 15 November 1939 based on adult franchise, and was accepted by the British in August 1940. ",
            "keyString": "475989s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term Brahmadeya occurs for the first time in",
            "optionA": "  early Vedic texts ",
            "optionB": "  early Buddhist texts ",
            "optionC": "  pre-Gupta inscriptions ",
            "optionD": "  post-Gupta inscriptions ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Brahmadeya occured the first time in pre-gupta inscriptions. ",
            "keyString": "560146s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under whose leadership was the all India Muslim League set up?",
            "optionA": "  Mohammed Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Sayyid Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Aga Khan ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1906, All India Muslim League was set up under the leader ship of Aga Khan, Nawab Salimullab of Dacca and Nawab Mohsin-ul-Mulk. The League supported the partition of Bengal, opposed the Swadeshi Movement, and demanded special safegurds for its community and a separate electorates of Muslims. This led to communal differences between Hindus and Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "560582s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Though Ashoka had many sons, the inscriptions mentioned only one who is not mentioned in any other source. He is",
            "optionA": "  Kunala ",
            "optionB": "  Tivara ",
            "optionC": "  Mahendra ",
            "optionD": "  Jalauka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTIVARAis the only son mentioned in the inscription. ",
            "keyString": "560835s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "We can know about early vedic period from",
            "optionA": "  archaeological  excavations ",
            "optionB": "  the Rig Veda ",
            "optionC": "  Jatak Katha ",
            "optionD": "  contemporary culture ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom Rig Veda, which is the earliest specimen of Indo -European language we know about the Aryans. The Rig Veda consists of ten mandalas or books. We can know about the early vedic period from Rig Veda. ",
            "keyString": "561061s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Upanishads are",
            "optionA": "  A source of Hindu philosophy ",
            "optionB": "  Books of ancient Hindu laws ",
            "optionC": "  Books on social behavior of man ",
            "optionD": "  Prayers to God ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Upanishads are a collection of texts of religious and philosophical nature, written in India probably between c. 800 BCE and c. 500 BCE, during a time when Indian society started to question the traditional Vedic religious order. ",
            "keyString": "561282s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which British Act was the provision to establish a Federation of India concession of Governor\u2019s provinces and Princely states made?",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act 1918 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act 1925 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act 1930 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India Act 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of India Act 1935 provision for the establishment of a \"Federation of India\", to be made up of both British India and some or all of the \"princely states\". ",
            "keyString": "651545s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Poona Pact between Mahatma Gandhi and Dr. B. R. Ambedkar signed?",
            "optionA": "  In 1920 ",
            "optionB": "  In 1925 ",
            "optionC": "  In 1928 ",
            "optionD": "  In 1932 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn agreement between Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi was signed 84 years ago on September 24, 1932. The agreement was signed by Pt Madan Mohan Malviya and Dr. B. R. Ambedkar and some Dalit leaders at Yerwada Central Jail in Pune, to break Mahathma Gandhi's fast unto death. ",
            "keyString": "652323s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The British Prime Minister Atlee announced the withdrawal of the Britishers in the House of Commons from India on",
            "optionA": "  February 20, 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  February 20, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  March 20, 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  March 20, 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Prime Minister of Britain Clement Atlee declared on February 20, 1947 in the House of Commons that the British would quit India after transferring power into the responsible hand not later than June 1948.",
            "keyString": "653120s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said, \u201cIndia is for Indians?\u201d",
            "optionA": "  Syed Hasan Imam ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. S.Gopal ",
            "optionD": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Dayanand Saraswati gave the political slogan that India is for Indians. Dayanand said \u2013 World is a battlefield where every individual has to work out his salvation by right deeds. ",
            "keyString": "653863s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said,\" One Country One God, One Caste, one Mind brothers all of us Without Difference, without Doubt ?\"",
            "optionA": "  V. ",
            "optionB": " Savarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Syed Hasan Imam ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tV. D. Savarkar said,\" One Country One God, One Caste, one Mind brothers all of us Without Difference, without Doubt \". ",
            "keyString": "654710s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded Abhinav Bharat ?",
            "optionA": "  V.",
            "optionB": "Savarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Arbindo Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinav Bharat was named after the Abhinav Bharat Society, an organisation founded by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar in 1904. ",
            "keyString": "809764s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The two names which were associates with the publication of the paper \u2018Yugantar\u2019 are:",
            "optionA": "  Barindra kumar Ghose and Arbindo Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Bhupendranath Dutta and Arbindo Ghosh ",
            "optionC": "  Barindra kumar Ghose and Bhupendranath Dutta ",
            "optionD": "  Arbindo Ghosh and V.",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe two names which were associates with the publication of the paper \u2018Yugantar\u2019 are Barindra kumar Ghose and Bhupendranath Dutta. ",
            "keyString": "810068s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Delhi was formally declared the future capital of the British India in :",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1909 ",
            "optionC": "  1912 ",
            "optionD": "  1911 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKing George V crowned in England in 1911. A durbar was held in Delhi to celebrate this occasion in India and Delhi was declared the capital of imperial India in that durbar. The foundation stone of the city was laid by George V, Emperor of India during the Delhi Durbar of 1911. ",
            "keyString": "810301s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The year which is associated with the Gadar movement is:",
            "optionA": "  1911 ",
            "optionB": "  1913 ",
            "optionC": "  1917 ",
            "optionD": "  1922 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, Pacific Coast Hindustan Association was founded by Lala Hardayal with Sohan Singh Bhakna as its president, which was called Ghadar Party. The members of this party were the immigrant Sikhs of US and Canada. The first issue of The Ghadar, was published from San Francisco on November 1, 1913. ",
            "keyString": "810533s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Queen Victoria assumed the title of the Empress of India in 1876 by :",
            "optionA": "  British parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Singaporian Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Royal Titles Bill was brought before Parliament in 1876. Queen Victoria opened Parliament in person, the first time since the death of Prince Albert, to announce the change in royal title.",
            "keyString": "810778s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From where did the quit India Movement begin?\n",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Pune ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1942 at the All-India Congress Committee session in Bombay, Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi launched the 'Quit India' movement. The next day, Gandhi, Nehru and many other leaders of the Indian National Congress were arrested by the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "936987s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Abhinav Bharat organized in 1904 was :",
            "optionA": "  Hindu Mahashabha ",
            "optionB": "  A secret society of revolutionary activists ",
            "optionC": "  All India Kisan Mahasabha ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinav Bharat was named after the Abhinav Bharat Society, an organisation founded by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar in 1904. The original organization believed in armed revolution, and was responsible for the assassinations of some officers of the ruling British government before being disbanded in 1952. ",
            "keyString": "938102s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major Muslim organizations which opposed the partition of India were",
            "optionA": "  The Jamiat-Ulema-hind ",
            "optionB": "  Khudai Khidmatgar ",
            "optionC": "  Majlis-e-Ahrar \u2013Hind ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major Muslim organizations which opposed the partition of India were The Jamiat-Ulema-hind, Khudai Khidmatgar and Majlis-e-Ahrar \u2013Hind. ",
            "keyString": "938779s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the selected as first satyagrahi by Mahatma Gandhi to begin individual satyagraha in 1940?",
            "optionA": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Brahma Datt ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress was in a confused state again after the August Offer. The radicals and leftists wanted to launch a mass Civil Disobedience Movement, but here Gandhi insisted on Individual Satyagraha. The first Satyagrahi selected was Acharya Vinoba Bhave, who was sent to Jail when he spoke against the war. ",
            "keyString": "939465s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the mastermind of bomb attack on Lord Hardinge at chandani chowk in Delhi in 1912?",
            "optionA": "  Amir Chand ",
            "optionB": "  Avadh Behari ",
            "optionC": "  Rasbihari Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Basant Kumar Biswas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the crisp morning of 23 December 1912, Delhi was decked up to welcome the then Viceroy Lord Hardinge on the occasion of the capital\u2019s transfer from Calcutta to Delhi. At a building in Chandni Chowk, a petite woman could be seen waiting with the crowd to see the Viceroy, and then a bomb exploded.Basant Biswas, a young boy of 16 years, had dressed up as a woman and thrown a crude bomb at the elephant carrying the Viceroy. Hardinge escaped with injuries. Rash Behari was the mastermind behind the attack and helped make the bomb. After the blast, Bose went back to his government job at the Forest Research Institute and even organised an honorary reception for Hardinge a few months later. ",
            "keyString": "940090s51m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main centre of Wahabi Movement  during the freedom movement was",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore ",
            "optionC": "  Patna ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis movement, centred around Patna was an Islamic revivalist movement, whose stress was to condemn any change into the original Islam and return to its true spirit. The movement was led by Syed Ahmed Barelvi. ",
            "keyString": "38718s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Dayanand established the head quarters of Arya Samaj in:",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Arya Samaj unit was formally set up by him at Bombay in 1875 and later the headquarters of the Samaj were established at Lahore. ",
            "keyString": "39384s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1912 Mohammad Ali started the paper",
            "optionA": "  The Native Opinion ",
            "optionB": "  The New India ",
            "optionC": "  Al-Balagh ",
            "optionD": "  The Comrade ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Comrade was a weekly English-language newspaper that was published and edited by Maulana Mohammad Ali between 1911 and 1914. ",
            "keyString": "40021s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National congress decided to launch an individual civil disobedience in place of Mass civil Disobedience in:",
            "optionA": "  1942 ",
            "optionB": "  1935 ",
            "optionC": "  1933 ",
            "optionD": "  1928 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National congress decided to launch an individual civil disobedience in place of Mass civil Disobedience in July 1933. ",
            "keyString": "40638s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Act provided for the establishment of an All India federation at the centre consisting of the provinces of British India and the princely states?",
            "optionA": "  The Government of India Act 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act 1918 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act 1925 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India Act 1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1935, This act ended the system of dyarchy introduced by GOI Act 1919 and provided for establishment of a Federation of India to be made up of provinces of British India and some or all of the Princely states. However, the federation never came into being as the required number of princely states did not join it. ",
            "keyString": "41243s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term yavanika meant",
            "optionA": "  Foreign goods ",
            "optionB": "  Dancer ",
            "optionC": "  Curtain ",
            "optionD": "  Theatre ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term yavanika meant curtain. ",
            "keyString": "101604s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term Khalisa in Mughal administration signified the",
            "optionA": "  entire Imperial establishment ",
            "optionB": "  land owned by the emperor himself ",
            "optionC": "  religious land grants ",
            "optionD": "  land from where revenue was collected for the Imperial Treasury ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Khalisa in Mughal administration signified the land owned by emperor himself. ",
            "keyString": "101638s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Visakhadatta sketches the event after the death of Samudragupta in his work",
            "optionA": "  Mudrarakasam ",
            "optionB": "  Devi Chand Guptam ",
            "optionC": "  Mrichekakatika ",
            "optionD": "  Malavikagnimitra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mudrarakshasa, a historical play in sanskrit by Vishakhadatta in late 4th or early 5th century narrates the ascent of the king Chandragupta Maurya to power in Northern India. ",
            "keyString": "101652s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of Dual Government during the latter half of the 18th century AD is associated with the name of",
            "optionA": "  Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  Waren Hastings ",
            "optionD": "  William Bentinck ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDual Government of Bengal started in 1765, when Clive concluded two separate 'treaties of Allahabad' with Shah Alam II(12 Aug.1765) & Shujauddaula(16 Aug.1765). Warren Hastings ended the dual system of government in 1772. ",
            "keyString": "101665s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vedas contain all the truth was interpreted by",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Dayananda ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vedas contain all the truth was interpreted by Swami Dayananda. ",
            "keyString": "101677s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kalinga was fought in",
            "optionA": "  321 BC ",
            "optionB": "  301 BC ",
            "optionC": "  261 BC ",
            "optionD": "  241 BC ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kalinga War was a war fought between the Mauryan Empire and the state of Kalinga. Kalinga was an important kingdom because it controlled the trade routes with Southeast Asia. Because of this, Ashoka, the Mauryan king, wanted to capture it. Therefore he lead his huge army to Kalinga in 261 BC. ",
            "keyString": "158582s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Government of India, Provincial Legislatures consisted of two chambers, except in the case of",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Government of India, Provincial Legislatures consisted of two chambers, except in the case was Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "158888s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Venetian traveler who travelled with his wife and reached Vijayanagar around 1420 was",
            "optionA": "  Athanasius Nikitin ",
            "optionB": "  Niccolo de Conti ",
            "optionC": "  Ibn Batuta ",
            "optionD": "  Ferishta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Venetian traveler who travelled with his wife and reached Vijayanagar around 1420 was Niccolo de Conti. ",
            "keyString": "159127s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The year 788 AD was a good one for Hinduism. Why?",
            "optionA": "  Shankracharya was born that year. ",
            "optionB": "  Harsha Vardhana, the last Buddhist king, died. ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta converted to Hinduism. ",
            "optionD": "  All Muslim invaders were defeated. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe year 788 AD was a good one for Hinduism because Shankracharya was born that year. ",
            "keyString": "159357s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Uprising of 1857 was described as the first Indian war of Independence by",
            "optionA": "  S.N. Sen ",
            "optionB": "  R.",
            "optionC": " Mazumdar ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian War of Independence is an Indian nationalist history of the 1857 revolt by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar that was first published in 1909. ",
            "keyString": "159576s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "About the formation of which organization A.O. Hume said \u201cA safety valve for the escape of great and growing forces generated by our own action urgently needed.\u201d",
            "optionA": "  Bhinav Bharat ",
            "optionB": "  Young Indian Organization ",
            "optionC": "  Young India ",
            "optionD": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Indian National Congress organization, A.O. Hume said \u201cA safety valve for the escape of great and growing forces generated by our own action urgently needed.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "249724s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The demand for Swarajya or self- government within the British empire was made from the Congress platform by",
            "optionA": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Both Gopal Krishna Gokhale and Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe demand for Swarajya or self- government within the British empire was made from the Congress platform by Gopal Krishna Gokhale in 1905 and Dadabhai Naoroji in 1906. ",
            "keyString": "249989s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi\u2019s first great experiment in Satyagraha came in 1917 in",
            "optionA": "  Ahemdabad ",
            "optionB": "  Champaran ",
            "optionC": "  Kheda ",
            "optionD": "  Dandi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Champaran Satyagraha of 1917 was the first Satyagraha movement inspired by Gandhi and a major revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. It was a farmer's uprising that took place in Champaran district of Bihar, India during the British colonial period. ",
            "keyString": "250222s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rehnumai Mazdayasan Sabha started in 1851 by Naoroji Furdonji, Dadabahi Naroji, S.S. Bengalee and other was a",
            "optionA": "  Parsi Economical Reform Association ",
            "optionB": "  Parsi education Reform Association ",
            "optionC": "  Parsi culture Reform Association ",
            "optionD": "  Parsi religious Reform Association ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRehnumai Mazdayasan Sabha started in 1851 by Naoroji Furdonji Dadabahi Naroji, S.S. Bengalee and other was a Parsi religious Reform Association. ",
            "keyString": "250442s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi gave the title of Sardar to Vallabhbhai Patel for his great organizational skill in:",
            "optionA": "  Kheda Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Champaran Satyagraha ",
            "optionC": "  The Bardoli Satyagraha ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi gave the title of Sardar to Vallabhbhai Patel for his great organizational skill in The Bardoli Satyagraha. ",
            "keyString": "250716s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lala Lajpat Rai was also known as :",
            "optionA": "  Sher-e-Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Sher-e-Maharastra ",
            "optionC": "  Sher-e-Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Sher-e-Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Lajpat Rai was born on 28 January 1865 in Dhudike (now Moga district) of Punjab. He was popularly known as Punjab Kesari meaning The Lion of Punjab also known as Sher-E- Punjab in Punjabi for his contribution to the freedom movement. ",
            "keyString": "314828s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sri Aurobindo Ghosh was born in the year :\n",
            "optionA": "  1872 ",
            "optionB": "  1982 ",
            "optionC": "  1884 ",
            "optionD": "  1892 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurobindo Ghose was born in India on 15th August 1872. At a young age, he was sent to England to be educated at St Paul's. Sri Aurobindo was an excellent student and won a scholarship to read classics at King's College Cambridge. ",
            "keyString": "314979s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Doctrine of Passive Resistance was published in the daily Vande Mataram in:",
            "optionA": "  April 1907 ",
            "optionB": "  April 1906 ",
            "optionC": "  April 1905 ",
            "optionD": "  April 1904 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDoctrine of Passive Resistance was published in the daily Vande Mataram in April 1907 by Sri Aurobindo Ghosh.",
            "keyString": "316215s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian People play people\u2019s role in the people\u2019s war was the slogan of:",
            "optionA": "  The Forward Block ",
            "optionB": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "optionC": "  Communist Party of India ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Communist Party of India had been formed in 1925. The key slogan of their party was to make the Indian People play a people's role in the people\u2019s war. ",
            "keyString": "378161s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1942 who appealed the Britishers to leave India in God\u2019s hands?",
            "optionA": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Mohhamad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar patel ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn May 1942, Mahatma Gandhi called on Britain to \u201cleave India to God. If this is too much then leave her to anarchy.\u201d In July 1942, the Congress Working Committee met at Wardha. The resolution demanded, \u201cThe British Rule in India must end immediately.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "378208s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Individual Satyagrah \u2013 symbolic and non-violent in nature was started on:",
            "optionA": "  October 17, 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  October 17, 1940 ",
            "optionC": "  October 17, 1939 ",
            "optionD": "  October 17, 1938 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Individual satyagraha movement started on 17th October, 1940 and continued upto December. ",
            "keyString": "378458s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which slogan was given by the Congress in opposition to British Government involving India in Second World War in 1939 without consulting the people of India ?",
            "optionA": "  Karo ya Maro ",
            "optionB": "  Nahi Karenge, Nahi Ladenge ",
            "optionC": "  Na koi bhai, na koi pai. ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNa koi bhai, na koi pai slogan was given by the Congress in opposition to British Government involving India in Second World War in 1939 without consulting the people of India. ",
            "keyString": "378600s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the elections held in 1937 under the provisions of the Government of India Act of 1935 Congress Ministries were formed in :",
            "optionA": "  Eleven States ",
            "optionB": "  Nine States ",
            "optionC": "  Five States ",
            "optionD": "  Ten States ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvincial elections were held in British India in the winter of 1936-37 as mandated by the Government of India Act 1935. Elections were held in eleven provinces - Madras, Central Provinces, Bihar, Orissa, United Provinces, Bombay Presidency, Assam, NWFP, Bengal, Punjab and Sindh. ",
            "keyString": "378729s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "United India House organizes Unity among Indians in the United states of America in",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1910 ",
            "optionD": "  1917 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnited India House organizes Unity among Indians in the United states of America in 1910. ",
            "keyString": "425256s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who in the year 1907 unfurled the first national flag at the International socialist conference in Stuttgart (Germany)?",
            "optionA": "  Madame Bhikaji Cama ",
            "optionB": "  Subash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhikaji Cama, also known as Madame Cama, was the first woman who successfully unfurled the first version of the tricolour Indian flag. She still remains to be one of the most prominent woman personalities to participate in the Indian Nationalist Movement. Born into very well-off Parsi family in Bombay (now Mumbai) Bhikaji received her early education there. ",
            "keyString": "425289s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1906 to protest discrimination against Indians in S. Africa Mahatma Gandhi started",
            "optionA": "  Satyagraha at Durban ",
            "optionB": "  Satyagraha at Cape Town ",
            "optionC": "  Satyagraha at Port Elizabeth ",
            "optionD": "  Satyagraha at Johannesburg ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA meeting in Johannesburg on 11 September 1906 marked the start of the resistance campaign, which ultimately became known as satyagraha (meaning \u2018truth-force\u2019), with its practitioners called satyagrahi. ",
            "keyString": "425303s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subhash Chandra Bose was elected the president of the Indian national congress :",
            "optionA": "  Ramgarh Session, 1940 ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Session, 1934 ",
            "optionC": "  Tripuri session, 1939 ",
            "optionD": "  Wardha Session, 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubhash Chandra Bose and Congress Tripuri Session 1939. The British Government was keen on Bose taking interest in the Axis Powers and the developing Gandhi Bose strife. In December 1938, Bose had a meeting with two representatives of the German Nazi Party. ",
            "keyString": "425315s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak began his drive for new awakening among the Indians by publishing two newspapers in 1881",
            "optionA": "  The Maratha  and Kesari ",
            "optionB": "  The Maratha  and Samwad ",
            "optionC": "  The Samwad and Kesari ",
            "optionD": "  The Maratha  and Kumudi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1881, he began his drive for new awakening by among the Indians publishing two newspapers i.e., the Maratha (English) and Kesari (Marathi). ",
            "keyString": "425327s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two of the great Mughals wrote their own memories. They were",
            "optionA": "  Babar and Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun and Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Babar and Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir and Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabar and Jahangir were two of the great Mughals wrote their own memories. ",
            "keyString": "477028s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which king belongs the Lion capital at Sarnath?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Harshavardhan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lion Capital of Ashoka is a sculpture of four Asiatic lions standing back to back, on an elaborate base that includes other animals. A graphic representation of it was adopted as the official Emblem of India in 1950. It was originally placed on the top of the Ashoka pillar at the important Buddhist site of Sarnath by the Emperor Ashoka, in about 250 BCE. The pillar, sometimes called the A\u015boka Column, is still in its original location, but the Lion Capital is now in the Sarnath Museum, in the state of Uttar Pradesh, India. ",
            "keyString": "477080s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The use of spinning wheel (Charkha) became common during the",
            "optionA": "  9th Century AD ",
            "optionB": "  10th Century AD ",
            "optionC": "  12th Century AD ",
            "optionD": "  14th Century AD ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe use of spinning wheel (Charkha) became common during the 14th Century AD. ",
            "keyString": "477310s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The language of discourses of Gautama Buddha was",
            "optionA": "  Bhojpuri ",
            "optionB": "  Magadhi ",
            "optionC": "  Pali ",
            "optionD": "  Sanskrit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe language discourses of Gautam Buddha was Pali. ",
            "keyString": "477474s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There were widespread risings against the British in the 1820s. Which one of the following did not revolt in the 1820s?",
            "optionA": "  Santhals ",
            "optionB": "  Ahoms ",
            "optionC": "  Pagal Panthis ",
            "optionD": "  Ramosi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere were widespread risings against the British in the 1820s. Santhals did not revolt in the 1820s. ",
            "keyString": "477607s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The weekly Commonweal was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Bipan Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter making Madras her home, Annie Besant founded a weekly newspaper Commonweal in January 1914. ",
            "keyString": "526372s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ustad Mansur was a famous painter in the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Shajahan ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUstad Mansur (flourished 1590-1624) was a seventeenth-century Mughal painter and court artist. He grew up during the reign of Jahangir (r. 1605 - 1627) during which period he excelled at depicting plants and animals. ",
            "keyString": "526413s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vedic deity Indra was the Goddess of",
            "optionA": "  Wind ",
            "optionB": "  Eternity ",
            "optionC": "  Rain and thunder ",
            "optionD": "  Fire ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Vedas, Indra is the king of Svarga (Heaven) and the Devas. He is the god of the heavens, lightning, thunder, storms, rains and river flows. Indra is the most referred to deity in the Rigveda. ",
            "keyString": "526428s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tolkappiyam is associated with the",
            "optionA": "  first Sangam period ",
            "optionB": "  second Sangam period ",
            "optionC": "  third Sangam period ",
            "optionD": "  post-third Sangam period ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ancient Tamil literature consists of the grammatical work Tolkappiyam in second Sangam period. ",
            "keyString": "526444s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pulakesin II was the most famous ruler of",
            "optionA": "  Chalukyas ",
            "optionB": "  Cholas ",
            "optionC": "  Pallavas ",
            "optionD": "  Satavahanas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPulakeshin II (IAST: Pulake\u015bin, r. c. 610-642 CE) was the most famous ruler of the Chalukya dynasty of Vatapi (present-day Badami in Karnataka, India). ",
            "keyString": "526457s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Montague - Chelmsford report was prepared on the basis of",
            "optionA": "  The Government of India act 1913 ",
            "optionB": "  The Government of India act, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  The Government of India act 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe reforms were outlined in the Montagu-Chelmsford Report prepared in 1918 and formed the basis of the Government of India Act 1919.These are related to constitutional reforms. ",
            "keyString": "573326s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Governor General who came to be known as father of communal electorate in India was",
            "optionA": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lainthgo ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Minto ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Minto was known as Father of communal electorate. ",
            "keyString": "573358s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In order to restrict the freedom of the press, the British government passed \"The Indian official secrets Act\" in",
            "optionA": "  1907 ",
            "optionB": "  1904 ",
            "optionC": "  1903 ",
            "optionD": "  1896 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian official secrets Act in 1904. ",
            "keyString": "573372s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most outstanding representative of Militant Nationalist School of thought was",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Bismil ",
            "optionD": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most outstanding representative of militant school was Bal Gangadhar Tilak later popularly known as Lokamanya Tilak. ",
            "keyString": "573384s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first economic thinker of India who showed through his writings that the basic cause of India\u2019s poverty lay in the British exploitation and drain of wealth was",
            "optionA": "  Badruddin Tyabji ",
            "optionB": "  Womesh Chandra Bonnerjee ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  N.G. Chandavarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDadabhai Naoroji was the first economic thinker of India. In his writings on economics, he showed that the basic cause of India's poverty lay in the British exploitation of India and the drain of its wealth. Dadabhai was honored by being thrice elected president of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "573395s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Barindra Kumar Ghose and Bhupendranath Dutta started:",
            "optionA": "  Jugantar ",
            "optionB": "  Som Prakash ",
            "optionC": "  Vichar Lahiri ",
            "optionD": "  Sandhya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBarindra Kumar Ghosh or Barindra Ghosh, or, popularly, Barin Ghosh (5 January 1880 \u2013 18 April 1959) was an Indian revolutionary and journalist. He was one of the founding members of Jugantar, a revolutionary outfit in Bengal. Barindra Ghosh was a younger brother of Sri Aurobindo. ",
            "keyString": "643713s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Curzon announced the partition of Bengal on :",
            "optionA": "  16 October , 1911 ",
            "optionB": "  16 October , 1896 ",
            "optionC": "  16 October , 1907 ",
            "optionD": "  16 October , 1905 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe decision to effect the Partition of Bengal was announced on 19 July 1905 by the Viceroy of India, Curzon. The partition took place on 16 October 1905 and separated the largely Muslim eastern areas from the largely Hindu western areas. ",
            "keyString": "649766s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose statement is this \u2013\u201cThe Indians should no longer be satisfied with mere mendicancy neither should they beg the English for concessions\u201d?\n",
            "optionA": "  V N Mandalik ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Abdul Kalam Azad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Lajpat Rai statement is this \u2013\u201cThe Indians should no longer be satisfied with mere mendicancy neither should they beg the English for concessions\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "651040s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian revolutionary was called by the Britishers as \u2018The Father of Indian Disaffection and biggest traitor\u2019?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Hardyal ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  M G Ranade ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak (23 July 1856 \u2013 1 August 1920), born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. The British colonial authorities called him \"The father of the Indian unrest.\" ",
            "keyString": "652049s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of a society known as \u2018Abhinav Bharat\u2019 ?",
            "optionA": "  J K Hikki ",
            "optionB": "  B B Upadhyay ",
            "optionC": "  Vinayak Damodar Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinav Bharat Society (Young India Society) was a secret society founded by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar and his brother Ganesh Damodar Savarkar in 1903. ",
            "keyString": "653993s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called Subhash Chandra Bose as Desh Nayak ? \n",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindranath Tagore called Subhash Chandra Bose as Desh Nayak. ",
            "keyString": "707985s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The prominent leaders of Indian Association which was established in Bengal in July 26, 1876 were : \n",
            "optionA": "  Anand Mohan Bose and Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "optionB": "  Sisir Kumar Ghosh and Kali Mohan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Kali Mohan Das and Shambhuchand  Mukherjee ",
            "optionD": "  Shambhuchand  Mukherjee and Jogesh Chandra Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Reform Association faction on July 26, 1876 established a Bharat Sabha with Bengali leaders like Surendranath Banerjee, Sivanath Sastri, Ananda Mohan Bose etc. and held its first annual conference in Calcutta. Initially under Sen it was pro-Crown. ",
            "keyString": "708019s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called Government India Act 1935 a Charter of Slavery ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Ballabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPt. Jawaharlal Nehru called Government India Act 1935 a Charter of Slavery. ",
            "keyString": "708034s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress passed Quit India Resolution at :\n",
            "optionA": "  Wardha Session, 1942. ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Session, 1934 ",
            "optionC": "  Tripuri Session, 1939 ",
            "optionD": "  Ramgarh Session, 1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1942 at the All-India Congress Committee session in Bombay, Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi launched the 'Quit India' movement. The next day, Gandhi, Nehru and many other leaders of the Indian National Congress were arrested by the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "708047s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wavell Plan- essentially dealing with Indian demand of self-rule and reconstitution of Viceroy's Council was put forth by Lord Wavell in:\n",
            "optionA": "  1935 ",
            "optionB": "  1942 ",
            "optionC": "   1945 ",
            "optionD": "  1943 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWavell Plan- essentially dealing with Indian demand of self-rule and reconstitution of Viceroy's Council was put forth by Lord Wavell in 1945.",
            "keyString": "708061s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which revolutionary was sentenced to death on August 17, 1909?\n",
            "optionA": "  Rash Bihari Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Sekhar Ajad ",
            "optionD": "  Madanlal Dhingra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadanlal Dhingra claimed that he had murdered Curzon-Wyllie as a patriotic act and in revenge for the inhumane killings of Indians by the British Government in India. He was found guilty and sentenced to death. He was executed at Pentonville Prison on 17 August 1909. ",
            "keyString": "752203s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded Tattvabodhini  sabha in 1839 ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Sarswati ",
            "optionB": "  Maharishi Devendranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Jogesh Chandra Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 6 October 1839 Debendranath Tagore established Tattvaranjini Sabha which was shortly thereafter renamed the Tattwabodhini (Truth-seekers) Sabha. Initially confined to immediate members of the Tagore family, in 2 years it mustered over 500 members. ",
            "keyString": "752236s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The eminent Bengali novelist and composer of national song Vande Mataram who aroused a new consciousness in the 19th century Bengal Society was :\n",
            "optionA": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay ",
            "optionC": "  Sarat Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBankim Chandra Chattopadhyay was born on June 27, 1838, in Naihati in West Bengal to an orthodox Bengali Brahmin family. He wrote the national song 'Vande Mataram', which was a part of his novel Anandamath (1882). It is a political novel depicting a Sanyasi army fighting the British soldiers. ",
            "keyString": "752250s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda established Ramakrishna Mission :\n",
            "optionA": "  In 1892 ",
            "optionB": "  In 1897 ",
            "optionC": "  In 1937 ",
            "optionD": "  In 1939 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamakrishna Mission was established on 1st May, 1897 bySwami Vivekananda with the twin objectives of working for one\u2019s own liberation as well as working for the welfare of the world at large. ",
            "keyString": "752262s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For the cause of national liberation Swami Dayananda stressed on :\n",
            "optionA": "  Swabhasha and Swarajya ",
            "optionB": "  Swadharma ",
            "optionC": "  Swadeshi ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor the cause of national liberation Swami Dayananda stressed on Swadeshi, Swadharma, Swabhasha and Swarajya.",
            "keyString": "752272s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said - \u201cOur Life and religion are useless without the attainment of Swaraj\u201d?",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Veer Kunwar ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1906, Bal Gangadhar Tilak introduced two slogans \u2018Swaraj is my birth right\u2019 and \u2018Our life and religion are useless without the attainment of Swaraj\u2019. ",
            "keyString": "787479s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The newspapers \u2018The Punjabi and The pupil\u2019 were published by :",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Lala Hardyal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe newspapers \u2018The Punjabi and The pupil\u2019 were published by Lala Lajpat Rai.",
            "keyString": "787511s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National College in Calcutta had been established on :",
            "optionA": "  September 14, 1906 ",
            "optionB": "  July 14, 1906 ",
            "optionC": "  March 14, 1906 ",
            "optionD": "  August 14, 1906 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBengal National College started with Sri Aurobindo as its first Principal on 14th August 1906.",
            "keyString": "787524s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1906 Dadabhai Naoroji had passed a resolution approving the issues of swadeshi and national education in:",
            "optionA": "  The Calcutta Session of the Indian National congress ",
            "optionB": "  The Lucknow Session of the Indian National congress ",
            "optionC": "  The Meerut Session of the Indian National congress ",
            "optionD": "  The Lahore Session of the Indian National congress ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe resolution of Swadeshi was adopted in 1906 Calcutta session of the Indian National Congress. This session was headed by Dada Bhai Naoroji. However, it was 1906 session at Calcutta in which four resolutions on self-government, boycott movement, Swadeshi and national education were passed by the Congress. ",
            "keyString": "787535s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who played an important role in the Gadar Movement in 1915?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  None of above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOriginal name of Ghadar Party was Pacific Coast Hindustan Association. The founding president of Ghadar Party was Sohan Singh Bhakna and Lala Hardayal was the co-founder of this party.",
            "keyString": "787547s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The third person who presented himself for individual Satyagrah launched by Mahatma Gandhi in October 1940 was:\n",
            "optionA": "  Brahma Datt ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  None of these  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Satyagrahi selected was Acharya Vinoba Bhave, who was sent to Jail when he spoke against the war. Second Satyagrahi was Jawahar Lal Nehru. Third was Brahma Datt, one of the inmates of the Gandhi\u2019s Ashram. ",
            "keyString": "829549s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Japan handed over Andaman Nicobar islands to Subhash Chandra Bose in Nov. 1943, he named these islands as : \n",
            "optionA": "  Shaheed Island and Samaj Island respectively ",
            "optionB": "  Samaj Island and Swaraj Island respectively ",
            "optionC": "  Swaraj  Island and Shaheed  Island respectively ",
            "optionD": "  Shaheed Island and Swaraj Island respectively ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Japan handed over Andaman Nicobar islands to Subhash Chandra Bose in Nov. 1943, he named these islands as Shaheed Island and Swaraj Island respectively. ",
            "keyString": "829581s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subhash Chandra Bose became the Supreme Commander of Indian National Army in :",
            "optionA": "  1932 ",
            "optionB": "  1935 ",
            "optionC": "  1943 ",
            "optionD": "  1945 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubhash Chandra Bose became the Supreme Commander of Indian National Army in 1943. Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose was born on 23rd January in 1897. He was an Indian nationalist who form the Indian National Army to fight against British Government. ",
            "keyString": "829595s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Mountbatten put forth the plan proposing the partition of India and the creation of Pakistan :\n",
            "optionA": "  On May 3, 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  On June 3, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  On July 3, 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  On August 3, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn June 3, 1947, immediately after his return to India, Lord mountbatten announced his plan for solving the \u2018present impasse\u2019. Before the plan was publicized, Lord Mountbattan had obtained the consent of the Congress and Sikh leaders and also of Mr. M.A. Jinnah. ",
            "keyString": "829607s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When quit India Resolution was passed in 1942, the Viceroy of India was : \n",
            "optionA": "  Lord Linlithgow ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Wavell ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Willingdon ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Linlithgow took his office on 18 April 1936 and leave on October 1, 1943. Cripps Mission visited India and Quit India resolution was passed in his tenure. ",
            "keyString": "829618s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who presided over the Karachi session of Indian National Congress in 1931 ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Sarojani Naydu ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Sardar  Vallabhbhai Patel. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Karachi session was presided by Sardar Patel. The congress adopted a resolution on Fundamental Rights and Economic Policy which represented the Party's Social, Economic and Political programme. It was later known as Karachi Resolution.",
            "keyString": "874740s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The congress nationalist party was formed to act as a powerful pressure group within the congress by:\n",
            "optionA": "  Madan Mohan Malviya and Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Mohan Malviya and M.S. Aney ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant and Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Bessant and Md. Ali Jinha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe congress nationalist party was formed to act as a powerful pressure group within the congress byMadan Mohan Malviya and M.S. Aney. ",
            "keyString": "874772s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rani Gaidinliu was a rebel leader against the Britishers from:\n\n",
            "optionA": "  Manipur ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pardesh ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRani Gaidinliu (26 January 1915 \u2013 17 February 1993) was a Rongmei Naga spiritual and political leader who led a revolt against British rule in India. The movement later turned into a political movement seeking to drive out the British from Manipur and the surrounding Naga areas. ",
            "keyString": "874785s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An interim cabinet headed by Jawaharlal Nehru was formed by the congress in :\n",
            "optionA": "  August 1940 ",
            "optionB": "  August 1943 ",
            "optionC": "  September 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  September 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe interim government of India was formed on September 2, 1946from the newly elected Constituent Assembly. ",
            "keyString": "874797s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolutionary who was associated with the Indian Independence League was :\n",
            "optionA": "  Rash Behari Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Rajguru ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRash Behari Bose was an Indian revolutionary noted for his planning of the Delhi-Lahore conspiracy of 1912 to assassinate the then Viceroy Lord Hardinge, and his involvement in the Ghadr Conspiracy of 1915. ",
            "keyString": "874808s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which session of the Indian National congress did the historic union of congress and Muslim League take place?\n",
            "optionA": "  Tripuri Session in 1939 ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore session in 1940 ",
            "optionC": "  Meerut Session in 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  Lucknow session in 1916 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLucknow Pact, (December 1916), agreement made by the Indian National Congress headed by Maratha leader Bal Gangadhar Tilak and the All-India Muslim League led by Muhammad Ali Jinnah; it was adopted by the Congress at its Lucknow session on December 29 and by the league on Dec. 31, 1916. ",
            "keyString": "916303s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League demanded a separate homeland for Indian Muslims for the first time at its :\n",
            "optionA": "  Lahore session in 1940. ",
            "optionB": "  Lucknow session in 1916 ",
            "optionC": "  Meerut Session 1946 ",
            "optionD": "  Tripuri Session in 1939 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was on this day in 1940 that the Muslim League, in its annual session held at Lahore, put forward the demand for a separate homeland for the Muslims of British India. Several Muslim League leaders spoke on the resolution before it was approved on March 24. ",
            "keyString": "916397s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian War of independence 1857 was written by :\n",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Jawahar Lal Neharu  ",
            "optionC": "  Damodar Chapekar ",
            "optionD": "  V.",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian War of Independence is an Indian nationalist history of the 1857 revolt by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar that was first published in 1909. ",
            "keyString": "916427s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Government of India act 1935 it was decided to establish a federation consisting of :\n",
            "optionA": "  Governor\u2019s provinces ",
            "optionB": "  Princely states ",
            "optionC": "  Governor\u2019s provinces and princely states ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Government of India act 1935 it was decided to establish a federation consisting of Governor\u2019s provinces and princely states. ",
            "keyString": "916451s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called Government of India Act 1935 as thoroughly rotten, fundamentally bad and totally unacceptable?  \n",
            "optionA": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Mohammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Balkrishana Chapekar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohammad Ali Jinnah commented it as \u201cthoroughly rotten, fundamentally bad and totally unacceptable\u201c. Jinnah\u2019s point of view was based upon the feeling that it would substantially increase Hindu majority at the center.",
            "keyString": "916474s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the major cause of discontent among soldiers before the revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  The Religious Cause ",
            "optionB": "  Question of promotion and pay ",
            "optionC": "  Political Cause ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuestion of promotion and pay was the major cause of discontent among soldiers before the revolt of 1857. ",
            "keyString": "954774s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Banga Darshan \u2013 a monthly magazine \u2013 was started in 1872 from Behrampur by:",
            "optionA": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "optionB": "  Umakant desai ",
            "optionC": "  Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBangadarshan was a Bengali literary magazine, founded by Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay in 1872, and resuscitated in 1901 under the editorship of Rabindranath Tagore. The magazine had a defining influence on the emergence of a Bengali identity and the genesis of nationalism in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "954805s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said about the British Government these words - \u201cYou do not realize how strong the government is if the congress challenges the government the government would finish it in five minutes?",
            "optionA": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Basant Kumar Biswas ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhale said about the British Government these words - \u201cYou do not realize how strong the government is if the congress challenges the government the government would finish it in five minutes\". ",
            "keyString": "954819s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which revolutionary said - \u201cfreedom is objective of our life and the Hindu religion would led us to the attainment of this objective?\u201d",
            "optionA": "   Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Narayan Guru ",
            "optionC": "  Dayanand Sarshwati ",
            "optionD": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurobindo Ghosh said - \u201cfreedom is objective of our life and the Hindu religion would led us to the attainment of this objective\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "954831s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the commander of 1857 revolt in Rohilkhand?",
            "optionA": "  Ahmadullah ",
            "optionB": "  Begum Hazrat Mahal ",
            "optionC": "  Jung Bahadur Rana ",
            "optionD": "  Tatya Tope ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAhmadullah Shah (1787 \u2013 5 June 1858) famous as Maulavi of Faizabad, was a leader of the Indian Rebellion of 1857. Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah was known as the Lighthouse of Rebellion in Awadh region. ",
            "keyString": "954842s52m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Partition of Bengal was revoked in 1911 during the Viceroyalty of",
            "optionA": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Reading  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Hardinge, the Viceroy of India (1910- 1916), is remembered for the annulment of the Partition of Bengal in 1911. ",
            "keyString": "29272s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Quit India movement began on:",
            "optionA": "  August 9, 1940 ",
            "optionB": "  August 9, 1941 ",
            "optionC": "  August 8, 1942 ",
            "optionD": "  August 9, 1944 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quit India Movement, or the August Movement, was a movement launched at the Bombay session of the All-India Congress Committee by Gandhiji on 8 August 1942, during World War II, demanding an end to British Rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "29304s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which document was the separate electorate granted for muslims ?",
            "optionA": "  Charter Act of 1813 ",
            "optionB": "  The Permanent Settlement ",
            "optionC": "  Mahalwari System Reforms ",
            "optionD": "  Morley Minto Reforms ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA momentous introduction in the reforms were the separate electorates where seats were reserved for Muslims and in which only Muslims would be polled. The implication that Muslims and their interests could only be protected by Muslims would influence Indian politics in the ensuing decades. The Muslim League had been founded in 1906 by an elite aiming to promote Muslim interests, prevent Hindu dominance over Muslims through a parliamentary system and to advance the Muslim perspective in the deliberations regarding constitutional reforms after October 1907. ",
            "keyString": "29317s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lucknow pact of 1916 was between:",
            "optionA": "  Indian Muslim League and Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Muslim League and Indian National congress ",
            "optionC": "  Indian National congress and Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Hardinge and Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lucknow Pact was an agreement that reached between the Indian National Congress and the Muslim League at the joint session of both the parties held in Lucknow in December 1916. Through the pact, the two parties agreed to allow overrepresentation to religious minorities in the provincial legislatures. ",
            "keyString": "29329s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the tenure of which Governor general was the resolution of total independence passed?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Reading ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Lahore session of 1929 {presided by Jawaharlal Nehru}, the congress passed a Poorna Swarajya Resolution {drafted by Jawaharlal Nehru} for complete independence. During this time, Lord Irwin was Governor general. ",
            "keyString": "29341s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which one of the following, the king exercised his control over villages in the Vijayanagar Empire?",
            "optionA": "  Dannayaka ",
            "optionB": "  Sumanta ",
            "optionC": "  Nayaka ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanayakacharya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThrough Mahanayakacharya, the king exercised his control over villages in the Vijayanagar Empire. ",
            "keyString": "66704s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vijayanagara ruler, Kirshnadev Raya's work Amuktamalyada, was in",
            "optionA": "  Telugu ",
            "optionB": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil ",
            "optionD": "  Kannada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vijayanagara ruler, Kirshnadev Rayas work Amuktamalyada, was in Telugu. ",
            "keyString": "66737s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under an agreement with which of the following countries did Subhas Chandra Bose organize the Indian soldiers, taken as prisoners by the Axis Powers, into the Azad Hind Fauj?",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Italy ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder an agreement with Japan Subhas Chandra Bose organize the Indian soldiers, taken as prisoners by the Axis Powers, into the Azad Hind Fauj. ",
            "keyString": "66752s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "We hear of two envoys being sent to the Roman kings, one in 27-28 AD to the court of Augustus and the other in 110-20 AD to the court of",
            "optionA": "  Cartius ",
            "optionB": "  Trajan ",
            "optionC": "  Nero ",
            "optionD": "  Brutus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe hear of two envoys being sent to the Roman kings , one in 27-28 AD to the court of Augustus and the other in 110-20 AD to the court of Trajan. ",
            "keyString": "66764s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The use of Kharoshti in ancient Indian architecture is the result of India's contact with",
            "optionA": "  Central Asia ",
            "optionB": "  Iran ",
            "optionC": "  Greece ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreece contact with India is the use of kharoshti architechture. ",
            "keyString": "66776s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Round Table conference was held on:",
            "optionA": "  December 12, 1930 ",
            "optionB": "  August 12, 1930 ",
            "optionC": "  April 12, 1930 ",
            "optionD": "  November 12, 1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Round Table Conference was first among the three such conferences organized between 1930 and 1932 by British government towards constitutional reforms in India. These conferences were conducted as per 1930 report of Simon Commission. First Round Table Conference was held between November 1930 and January 1931. It was officially inaugurated on November 12, 1930 at House of Lords at London by the British King (George V) and was chaired by then British Prime Minister, Ramsay MacDonald. ",
            "keyString": "103713s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Gandhi-Irvin pact under which Mahatma Gandhi agreed to suspend the civil Disobedience Movement was signed on",
            "optionA": "  March 5, 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  April 8, 1931 ",
            "optionC": "  May 8, 1931 ",
            "optionD": "  August 8, 1931 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi-Irwin Pact, agreement signed on March 5, 1931, between Mohandas K. Gandhi, leader of the Indian nationalist movement, and Lord Irwin (later Lord Halifax), British viceroy (1926\u201331) of India. ",
            "keyString": "103745s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With the objective of raising the moral and material status of the untouchables Dr. B.R. Ambedkar organized:",
            "optionA": "  The Harijan Hitkari sabha ",
            "optionB": "  The Bahishkrit Hitkari sabha ",
            "optionC": "  The Harijan Uthan sabha ",
            "optionD": "  The Bahishkrit Utthan sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWith the objective of raising the moral and material status of the untouchables Dr. B.R. Ambedkar organized The Bahishkrit Hitkari sabha in July 1924. ",
            "keyString": "103759s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which report became the basis for enacting the Government of India Act 1935?\n",
            "optionA": "  Reading's report ",
            "optionB": "  Montague Chelmsford Declaration ",
            "optionC": "  Morley Minto Reforms ",
            "optionD": "  Simon Commission\u2019s report ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India Act 1935 derived material from four key sources viz. Report of the Simon Commission, discussions at the Third Round Table Conference, the White Paper of 1933 and the reports of the Joint select committees. ",
            "keyString": "103771s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The committee headed by Motilal Nehru constituted to draw up a blue print for the future constitution of India published",
            "optionA": "  Nehru Report ",
            "optionB": "  Constitution report ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Report ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nehru Report of 28-30 August, 1928 was a memorandum outlining a proposed new dominion status constitution for India. It was prepared by a committee of the All Parties Conference chaired by Motilal Nehru with his son Jawaharlal Nehru acting as secretary. There were nine other members in this committee. ",
            "keyString": "103782s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Velu Thampi led a revolt against the British in state of",
            "optionA": "  Travancore ",
            "optionB": "  Baroda ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Mysore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVelayudhan Chempakaraman Thampi (1765\u20131809) was the Dalawa or Prime Minister of the Indian kingdom of Travancore between 1802 and 1809 during the reign of Bala Rama Varma Kulasekhara Perumal. He is best known for being one of the earliest individuals to rebel against the British East India Company's supremacy in India. ",
            "keyString": "143646s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mountbatten Plan of 1947 the people of ___ were given the right to decide through a plebiscite whether they wished to join Pakistan or India.",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  N.W.F.P and the Sylhet district of Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mountbatten Plan of 1947 the people of N.W.F.P and the Sylhet district of Assam were given the right to decide through a plebiscite whether they wished to join Pakistan or India. ",
            "keyString": "143680s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Three major powers that emerged in southern India in the 7th century AD were\nI. Cheras\nII. Cholas\nIII. Chalukyas\niV. Pallavas\nV. Pandyas",
            "optionA": "  I, II, V ",
            "optionB": "  II, III, IV ",
            "optionC": "  III, IV, V ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThree majorpowers that emerged in southern India in the 7th century AD were Cheras, Cholas and Pandyas. ",
            "keyString": "143695s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term 'Yavanapriya' mentioned in ancient Sanskrit texts denoted",
            "optionA": "  Ivory ",
            "optionB": "  Pepper ",
            "optionC": "  A fine variety of Indian muslin ",
            "optionD": "  Damsels sent to the Greek court for dance performance ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term 'Yavanapriya' mentioned in ancient Sanskrit texts denoted pepper. ",
            "keyString": "143713s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Timariots Governors and the Revenue Contractors, on their part reason in this manner: \"Why should the neglected state of this land create uneasiness in our minds and why should we expend our money and time to render it fruitful? We may be deprived of it in a single moment, and our exertions would benefit neither ourselves nor our children.\" This statement was made by",
            "optionA": "  Monserrate ",
            "optionB": "  Tavernier ",
            "optionC": "  Manrique ",
            "optionD": "  Bernier ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Timariots Governors and the Revenue Contractors, on their part reason in this manner: \"Why should the neglected state of this land create uneasiness in our minds and why should we expend our money and time to render it fruitful? We may be deprived of it in a single moment, and our exertions would benefit neither ourselves nor our children.\" This statement was made by Bernier. ",
            "keyString": "143725s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the suspension of the Non-Cooperation Movement, who were called pro-changers in the Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru and Anne Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Anne Besant and Chittranjan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Motilal Nehru and Chittranjan Das ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sudden withdrawal of the Non Cooperation Movement left congress with no other such programmes. There was an impatient section of the leaders in Congress whose expectations were wrapped up in the coming up elections in India in 1923, so that they enter into the legislatures and bring \u201cchange\u201d. These elections had to be conducted as per the provisions of the Government of India Act 1919. ",
            "keyString": "179726s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subhash Chandra Bose formed Forward Block in :",
            "optionA": "  The Year 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  The Year 1939 ",
            "optionC": "  The Year 1937 ",
            "optionD": "  The Year 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe All India Forward Block (AIFB) is a left-wing nationalist political party in India. It emerged as a faction within the Indian National Congress in 1939, led by Subhas Chandra Bose. The party re-established as an independent political party after the independence of India. ",
            "keyString": "179759s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called the 1857 revolt as \u2018Student Farmer-Middle class Revolt\u2019?",
            "optionA": "  Sumit Sarkar ",
            "optionB": "  Barun De ",
            "optionC": "  B A Saletore ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Amba Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. Amba Prasad called the 1857 revolt as \u2018Student Farmer-Middle class Revolt\u2019. ",
            "keyString": "179773s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Justice C. Y. Chintamani called Government of India Act 1935?",
            "optionA": "  Lazy Duck ",
            "optionB": "  Lame Duck ",
            "optionC": "  Lazy Federation ",
            "optionD": "  Lame Federation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJustice C. Y. Chintamani called Government of India Act 1935 a Lame Federation. ",
            "keyString": "179785s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi considered preconditions as necessary for a satyagrahi to fulfill namely :",
            "optionA": "  Follow truth and cultivate fearlessness. ",
            "optionB": "  Prefect Chastity ",
            "optionC": "  Adopts poverty ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi considered preconditions as necessary for a satyagrahi to fulfill namely Prefect Chastity, adopts poverty, follow truth and cultivate fearlessness. ",
            "keyString": "179796s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ultimate ownership of land during the post-Gupta period lay with",
            "optionA": "  The cultivator ",
            "optionB": "  The village community ",
            "optionC": "  The king ",
            "optionD": "  The joint family ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKing has the ultimate ownership of land during the post gupta period. ",
            "keyString": "217352s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which of the republic of Buddha belong?",
            "optionA": "  Licchavis ",
            "optionB": "  Sakyas ",
            "optionC": "  Mallas ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddha belong to Sakyas republic. ",
            "keyString": "217383s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There was a sharp class division at Harappa and Mohenjodaro. This is clear from the",
            "optionA": "  Indus seals excavated ",
            "optionB": "  Religious beliefs of the Harappans ",
            "optionC": "  Tools and implements used by the Harappans ",
            "optionD": "  Different types of dwellings excavated ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere was a sharp class division at Harappa and Mohenjodaro. This is clear from the Different types of dwellings excavated. ",
            "keyString": "217396s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The title given by the British Government to Mahatma Gandhi which he surrendered during the non-cooperation movement was",
            "optionA": "  Hind Keasri ",
            "optionB": "  Kaiser-e-Hind ",
            "optionC": "  Rai Bahadur ",
            "optionD": "  Rt. Honorable ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaiser-e-hind was the title given by british to Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "217408s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tipu sultan was the ruler of",
            "optionA": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionB": "  Madurai ",
            "optionC": "  Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  Vijayanagar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTipu Sultan (born Sultan Fateh Ali Sahab Tipu, 20 November 1750 \u2013 4 May 1799), also known as the Tipu sahab was a ruler of the Kingdom of Mysore. He was the eldest son of Sultan Hyder Ali of Mysore. ",
            "keyString": "217419s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vaikhanasa the five-fold conception of Vishnu consists of  brahmanpurushaprakritisatyaachyutaaniruddha",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III, IV and V ",
            "optionB": "  II, III, IV, V and VI ",
            "optionC": "  I, II, IV, V and VI ",
            "optionD": "  I, III, IV, V and VI ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVaikhanasa the five-fold conception of Vishnu consists of Brahman, Prakriti, Satya, Achutya and Annirudha. ",
            "keyString": "255374s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The troops raised by the emperor but not paid directly the state and place under the charge of mansabadars were known as",
            "optionA": "  Walashahi ",
            "optionB": "  Barawardi ",
            "optionC": "  Jcumaki ",
            "optionD": "  Dakhili ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe troops raised by the emperor but not paid directly the state and place under the charge of mansabadars were known as Dakhili. ",
            "keyString": "255457s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The treaty of Mangalore was signed between",
            "optionA": "  the English East India Company and Haidar Ali ",
            "optionB": "  the English East India Company and Tipu Sultan ",
            "optionC": "  Haidar Ali and the Zamorin of Calicut ",
            "optionD": "  the French East India Company and Tipu Sultan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTreaty of Mangalore. The Treaty of Mangalore was signed between Tipu Sultan and the British East India Company on 11 March 1784. It was signed in Mangalore and brought an end to the Second Anglo-Mysore War. ",
            "keyString": "255478s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To conquer and annex Peshawar and Punjab, Mahmud of Ghazni defeated",
            "optionA": "  Ghurids ",
            "optionB": "  Arabs ",
            "optionC": "  Karkotakas ",
            "optionD": "  Hindushahis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo conquer and annex Peshawar and Punjab, Mahmud of Ghazni defeated Hindushahis. ",
            "keyString": "255497s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which professions earlier leaders who struggled for freedom of India mainly belonged?",
            "optionA": "  Lawyers ",
            "optionB": "  Teachers ",
            "optionC": "  Journalists ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEarlier leaders who struggled for freedom of India mainly belonged to Lawyers, Teachers and Journalists. ",
            "keyString": "255514s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the founder of Haryanka Dynasty?\n",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Harshvardhan ",
            "optionC": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionD": "  Ghananand ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInitially, the capital was Rajagriha. Later, it was shifted to Pataliputra, near the present-day Patna in India. The founder of this dynasty was Bimbisara himself. According to the Buddhist text, the Mahavamsa, Bimbisara was anointed king by his father at the age of fifteen. ",
            "keyString": "294964s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolutionary like Ashfaqullah Khan, Chandra Shekhar  Azad, Ram Prasad Bismil, Roshan Singh and Rajendra Lahiri were all associated with : \n",
            "optionA": "  The Kakori Conspiracy case (1925) ",
            "optionB": "  1857 Revolt ",
            "optionC": "  Chauri Chaura Case ",
            "optionD": "  The Jallianwala Bagh massacre ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kakori Conspiracy (or Kakori train robbery or Kakori Case) was a train robbery that took place between Kakori and, near Lucknow, on 9 August 1925 during the Indian Independence Movement against the British Indian Government. The robbery was organised by Hindustan Republican Association (HRA). ",
            "keyString": "294997s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Moplah Rebellion in 1921 in Malabar was Muslim Peasants Rabellion against :\n",
            "optionA": "  Muslim Land Holders ",
            "optionB": "  The British Government Authority ",
            "optionC": "  The non-tribal outsiders ",
            "optionD": "  Hindu Land Holders ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHindu Land Holders. The Malabar rebellion (also known as the Moplah rebellion and M\u0101ppila Laha\u1e37a in Malayalam) was an armed uprising in 1921 against British authority in the Malabar region of Southern India by Mappilas and the culmination of a series of Mappila revolts that recurred throughout the 19th century and early 20th century. ",
            "keyString": "295011s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rowlatt Act was passed in : \n",
            "optionA": "  1905 ",
            "optionB": "  1913 ",
            "optionC": "  1919 ",
            "optionD": "  1925 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Anarchical and Revolutionary Crimes Act of 1919 , popularly known as the Rowlatt Act or Black Act, was a legislative act passed by the Imperial Legislative Council in Delhi on 10 March 1919, indefinitely extending the emergency measures of preventive indefinite detention, incarceration without trial and judicial review enacted in the Defence of India Act 1915 during the First World War. ",
            "keyString": "295022s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma  Gandhi launched Kheda Satyagrah on Gujrat in 1918 to support the cause of : \n",
            "optionA": "  Mill Owners ",
            "optionB": "  Land Lords ",
            "optionC": "  The peasants ",
            "optionD": "  Kol Rebellion  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kheda Satyagraha of 1918, in the Kheda district of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a Satyagraha movement organized by Mohandas Gandhi. It was a major revolt in the Indian independence movement. It was the third Satyagraha movement after Champaran Satyagraha and Ahmedabad mill strike. Gandhi organised this movement to support peasants of the Kheda district. People of Kheda were unable to pay the high taxes levied by the British due to crop failure and a plague epidemic. ",
            "keyString": "295033s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has written about the revolt of 1857- \u2018this was an eruption of social volcano\u2019 where many spent forces found vent. After the vent the whole social topography has changed. The scars of rebellion remained deep and shining?\u201d",
            "optionA": "  Brahma Datt ",
            "optionB": "  V. ",
            "optionC": " Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Gopal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshok Mehta has written about the revolt of 1857- \u2018this was an eruption of social volcano\u2019 where many spent forces found vent. After the vent the whole social topography has changed. The scars of rebellion remained deep and shining\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "332553s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Act may be regarded as the beginning of representative system in modern India?",
            "optionA": "  The Indian councils Act 1861 ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act 1918 ",
            "optionC": "  Government of India Act 1925 ",
            "optionD": "  Government of India Act 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian councils Act 1861 may be regarded as the beginning of representative system in modern India. ",
            "keyString": "332585s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Act may be the British parliament did Queen Victoria assume the title of \u2018the Empress of India\u2019 to emphasize British sovereignty over the whole of British provinces in India and Indian states?",
            "optionA": "  The Royal Titles Act 1866 ",
            "optionB": "  The Royal Titles Act 1870 ",
            "optionC": "  The Royal Titles Act 1876 ",
            "optionD": "  The Royal Titles Act 1886 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Royal Titles Act 1876 (39 & 40 Vict., c. 10) was an Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom which officially recognized Queen Victoria as \"Empress of India.\" ",
            "keyString": "332599s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vernacular press Act as a safety valve against vernacular newspapers was passed by Lord Lytton on",
            "optionA": "  April 14, 1878 ",
            "optionB": "  March 14, 1878 ",
            "optionC": "  March 14, 1876 ",
            "optionD": "  March 14, 1870 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe act was proposed by Lord Lytton, then Viceroy of India, and was unanimously passed by the Viceroy's Council on 14 March 1878. ",
            "keyString": "332612s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first to call the revolt of 1857 as an organized war for national Independence?",
            "optionA": "  Ashok Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. S Gopal ",
            "optionC": "  Syed Hasan Imam ",
            "optionD": "  V. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tV. D. Savarkar was the first to call the revolt of 1857 as an organized war for national Independence. ",
            "keyString": "332626s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom did the Britishers call the father of Indian disaffection and the biggest traitor?",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak (23 July 1856 \u2013 1 August 1920), born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. The British colonial authorities called him \"The father of the Indian unrest.\" He was also conferred with the title of \"Lokmanya\", which means \"accepted by the people (as their leader)\". ",
            "keyString": "371717s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established in 1893 the society for the removal of Obstacles to the Hindu Religion?",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Sarshawati ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Rai ",
            "optionC": "  The Chapekar brothers ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey organized an association called \u201cChapekar Club\u201d for physical and military training which they also calledas \u201cthe society for the removal of obstacles to the Hindu Religion\u201d. Their activities took the form of attacking leading social reformers in the dark, putting tar on the Queen\u2019s statue near the Esplanade in Bombay and burning the examination pandal. They became active members of the Ganapati melas the lustily sang songs praising Shivaji for \u201chis daring deeds and exhorting the audienceto risk their life on the battlefield in a national war to shed upon the earth the lifeblood of the enemies who destroyed Hindu religion\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "371783s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Rammohan Roy founded Brahma samaj on",
            "optionA": "  20 August,1838 ",
            "optionB": "  20 August,1828 ",
            "optionC": "  20 August,1848 ",
            "optionD": "  20 August,1858 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Session of Ram Mohan Roy's Brahmo Samaj is held in Kolkata. On 20th August 1828, the first session of Raja Ram Mohan Roy's Brahmo Samaj was held in Kolkata. Raja Ram Mohan Roy was a popular social and educational reformer in India who paved the way for progress in India under British rule. ",
            "keyString": "371800s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhiji launched the Non-cooperation movement in:",
            "optionA": "  The year 1910 ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1915 ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1917 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1920 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe non-cooperation movement was launched on 1 August 1920 and withdrawn in February 1922 after the Chauri Chaura incident. ",
            "keyString": "371817s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati was the first president of",
            "optionA": "  All India Hindu Mahasabha ",
            "optionB": "  All India Unity Mahasabha ",
            "optionC": "  All India Kisan Mahasabha ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Kisan Sabha(AIKS) is the peasant or farmers' wing of the Communist Party of India. The Kisan Sabha movement started in Bihar under the leadership of Swami Sahajanand Saraswati, who had formed in 1929 the Bihar Provincial Kisan Sabha (BPKS) to mobilise peasant grievances against the zamindari attacks on their occupancy rights. Gradually the peasant movement intensified and spread across the rest of India. All these radical developments on the peasant front culminated in the formation of the All India Kisan Sabha (AIKS) at the Lucknow session of the Indian National Congress in April 1936, with Swami Sahajanand Saraswati elected as its first president. ",
            "keyString": "371834s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Zabti System of revenue was prevalent during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Babar ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Todar Mal, as finance minister of Akbar, brought new system of revenue collection known as zabti system and dahshala system which was a system of taxation. Under the system he took a careful survey of crop yields and prices cultivated for a period of 10 years. ",
            "keyString": "397632s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The victories of Karikala are well portrayed in",
            "optionA": "  Palamoli ",
            "optionB": "  Aruvanad ",
            "optionC": "  Pattinappalai ",
            "optionD": "  Padirrupattu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe victories of Karikala are well portrayed in Pattinappalai. ",
            "keyString": "438628s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Todar Mal was associated with",
            "optionA": "  music ",
            "optionB": "  literature ",
            "optionC": "  land revenue reforms ",
            "optionD": "  law ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTodar Mal was associated with land revenue reforms. Raja Todar Mal was the Finance Minister of the Mughal empire during Akbar's reign. He was one of the Navaratnas in Akbar's durbar. ",
            "keyString": "438660s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The title of 'Viceroy' was added to the office of the Governor-General of India for the first time in",
            "optionA": "  1848 AD ",
            "optionB": "  1856 AD ",
            "optionC": "  1858 AD ",
            "optionD": "  1862 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe title of viceroy was added to the office of the Governer- general of India for the first time in 1858 A.D. ",
            "keyString": "438673s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which of the following dynasties did King Bhoja, a great patron of literature and art, belong?",
            "optionA": "  Karkota ",
            "optionB": "  Utpala ",
            "optionC": "  Paramara ",
            "optionD": "  Gurjara Pratihara ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhoja (reigned c. 1010\u20131055 CE) was an Indian king from the Paramara dynasty. His kingdom was centered around the Malwa region in central India, where his capital Dhara was located. Bhoja fought wars with nearly all his neighbours in attempts to extend his kingdom, with varying degrees of success. At its zenith, his kingdom extended from Chittor in the north to upper Konkan in the south, and from the Sabarmati River in the west to Vidisha in the east. ",
            "keyString": "438686s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vikramaditya, a king of Ujjain, started the Vikrama samvat in 58 BC in commemoration of his victory over",
            "optionA": "  Indo-Greeks ",
            "optionB": "  Sakas ",
            "optionC": "  Parthinas ",
            "optionD": "  Kushanas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVikramaditya, a king of Ujjain, started Vikrama Samvat era in 58 BCE after defeating the Shakas, and those who believe that he is based on a historical figure place him around the first century BCE. However, this era is identified as \"Vikrama Samvat\" after the ninth century CE. Other scholars believe that Vikramaditya is a mythical character, since several legends about him are fantastic in nature. ",
            "keyString": "438698s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tripitakas are sacred books of",
            "optionA": "  Buddhists ",
            "optionB": "  Hindus ",
            "optionC": "  Jains ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTripitaka is a Sanskrit word meaning Three Baskets. The sacred book of Buddhism is called the Tripitaka (called Tipitaka in Pali). ",
            "keyString": "487569s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The trident-shaped symbol of Buddhism does not represent",
            "optionA": "  Nirvana ",
            "optionB": "  Sangha ",
            "optionC": "  Buddha ",
            "optionD": "  Dhamma ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNirvana because in buddhism trident shaped symbol is a reference to the triple gem bhuddha ,dhamma and sangha. ",
            "keyString": "487645s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The theory of economic drain of India during British imperialism was propounded by",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  R.",
            "optionD": " Dutt ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe theory of economic drain of India during British imperialism was propounded by Dadabhai Naoroji. ",
            "keyString": "487662s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The treaty of Srirangapatna was signed between Tipu Sultan and",
            "optionA": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  Dalhousie ",
            "optionD": "  Warren Hastings ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Treaty of Srirangapatinam (also called Sri Ranga Patanam or Srirangapatna), signed 18 March 1792, ended the Third Anglo-Mysore War. Its signatories included Lord Cornwallis on behalf of the British East India Company, representatives of the Nizam of Hyderabad and the Maratha Empire, and Tipu Sultan, the ruler of Mysore. ",
            "keyString": "487688s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of competitive examination for civil service was accepted in principle in the year",
            "optionA": "  1833 ",
            "optionB": "  1853 ",
            "optionC": "  1858 ",
            "optionD": "  1882 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharter act 1853 Introduced open competition system for recruitment of civil servants. It was open for Indians also for the first time. Accordingly, Macaulay committee (committee on Indian civil service) was appointed in 1854. ",
            "keyString": "487706s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did Mahatma Gandhi go on fast unto death for the first time?",
            "optionA": "  1921 ",
            "optionB": "  1917 ",
            "optionC": "  1918 ",
            "optionD": "  1915 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1918, Gandhiji fought for the rights of the textile mill workers of Ahmedabad. Here for the first time he introduced a method of arbitration - fasting. ",
            "keyString": "533048s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is called the magna carta of Western Education system in Indian?",
            "optionA": "  Dispatch of Charles wood secretary of state 1854 ",
            "optionB": "  Slavery Bill for Education ",
            "optionC": "  Wonder of Education refoms ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWood's Dispatch / Despatch is known as Magna Carta (Magna Charta) of Indian Education. Wood's Dispatch was an act of 1854 implemented by the British rulers during pre-independent India. The despatch was presented by Sir Charles Wood to the directors of the British East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "533079s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who led the revolt of 1857 in Lucknow?",
            "optionA": "  Bahadur Shah Jafar ",
            "optionB": "  Jung Bahadur Rana ",
            "optionC": "  Begum Hazrat Mahal ",
            "optionD": "  Tatya Tope ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Indian Mutiny, from 1857 to 1858, Begum Hazrat Mahal's band of supporters, led by Raja Jailal Singh, rebelled against the forces of the British; later, they seized control of Lucknow and she declared her son, Birjis Qadra, as the ruler (Wali) of Oudh. ",
            "keyString": "533094s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \u201cone religion one caste and one God for mankind?\u201d",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Sarshwati ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Sachidanand Sarshwati ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Ramanand Sarshwati ",
            "optionD": "  Narayan Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Narayana Guru preached the doctrine of 'One caste, One religion, One God.' Its worth note that one of his athiest disciples, Sahadaran Ayyapan, changed into 'no religion, no caste and no God for mankind. ",
            "keyString": "533107s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On what ground did the second split in the congress take place in 1918?",
            "optionA": "  Charter act of India ",
            "optionB": "  Montague Chelmsford Declaration ",
            "optionC": "  Morley Minto Reforms ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress in a special session (August 1918) criticized the August Declaration as \u201cdisappointing and unsatisfactory\u201d and suggested important modifications. The Moderates, led by Surendra Nath Banerjee, supported the Declaration in a separate conference (November 1918). ",
            "keyString": "533118s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kakori Conspiracy took place in :",
            "optionA": "  1925 ",
            "optionB": "  1922 ",
            "optionC": "  1920 ",
            "optionD": "  1915 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kakori Conspiracy (or Kakori train robbery or Kakori Case) was a train robbery that took place between Kakori and, near Lucknow, on 9 August 1925 during the Indian Independence Movement against the British Indian Government. The robbery was organised by Hindustan Republican Association (HRA). ",
            "keyString": "569337s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre in Amritsar took place on :",
            "optionA": "  March 13, 1919 ",
            "optionB": "  April 13, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  May 13, 1919 ",
            "optionD": "  June 13, 1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jallianwala Bagh massacre, also known as the Amritsar massacre, took place on 13 April 1919 when troops of the British Indian Army under the command of Colonel Reginald Dyer fired rifles into a crowd of Punjabis, who had gathered in Jallianwala Bagh, Amritsar, Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "569369s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom did Mahatma Gandhi consider his political guru?",
            "optionA": "  Shri Bharat Kumar ",
            "optionB": "  Purushottam Das Tandon ",
            "optionC": "  Sir William Wedderburn ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishna Gokhale CIE pronunciation (9 May 1866 \u2013 19 February 1915) was an Indian political leader and a social reformer during the Indian Independence Movement. ",
            "keyString": "569382s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who brought out a paper with the title of the \u2018loyal Muhammadanans of India\u2019 ?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Sayyid Ahmad Khan. ",
            "optionB": "  Khan Abdul Ghafar Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Abbas Tyabji ",
            "optionD": "  Rafi Ahmed Kidwai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Sayyid Ahmad Khan brought out a paper with the title of the \u2018loyal Muhammadanans of India\u2019. ",
            "keyString": "611420s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Individual Satyagrah was started on:\n",
            "optionA": "  October 17, 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  October 17, 1939 ",
            "optionC": "  October 17, 1940 ",
            "optionD": "  October 17, 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn October 17, 1940, the Father of the Nation, Mahatma Gandhi had chosen Acharya Vinoba Bhave as the first satyagrahi (proponent of satyagraha) to start personal satyagraha (movement which meant holding to the truth) and Jawaharlal Nehru as the second. ",
            "keyString": "611452s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In order to secure co-operation of Indians the British government in the midst of worsening wartime international situation sent Cripps Mission to India:\n",
            "optionA": "  In 1940 ",
            "optionB": "  In 1942 ",
            "optionC": "  In 1945 ",
            "optionD": "  In 1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cripps mission was an attempt in late March 1942 by the British government to secure full Indian cooperation and support for their efforts in World War II. The mission was headed by Sir Stafford Cripps, a senior left-wing politician and government minister in the War Cabinet of Prime Minister Winston Churchill. ",
            "keyString": "611466s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In accordance with provisions of the Government of India Act  1935 elections to the Provincial Legislatures were held in  :",
            "optionA": "  February 1925 ",
            "optionB": "  February 1932 ",
            "optionC": "  February 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  February 1937 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvincial elections were held in British India in the winter of 1936-37 as mandated by the Government of India Act 1935. Elections were held in eleven provinces - Madras, Central Provinces, Bihar, Orissa, United Provinces, Bombay Presidency, Assam, NWFP, Bengal, Punjab and Sindh. The final results of the elections were declared in February 1937. ",
            "keyString": "611478s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The First Round Table Conference was held on: ",
            "optionA": "  November 12, 1930 ",
            "optionB": "  December 12, 1930 ",
            "optionC": "  November 12, 1937 ",
            "optionD": "  October 12, 1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Round Table Conference was held between November 1930 and January 1931. It was officially inaugurated on November 12, 1930 at House of Lords at London by the British King (George V) and was chaired by then British Prime Minister, Ramsay MacDonald. ",
            "keyString": "611489s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The East India Association was set up in : \n",
            "optionA": "  1866  ",
            "optionB": "  1857 ",
            "optionC": "  1836 ",
            "optionD": "  1885 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East India Association was founded by Dadabhai Naoroji in 1866, in collaboration with Indians and retired British officials in London. It superseded the London Indian Society and was a platform for discussing matters and ideas about India, and to provide representation for Indians to the Government. ",
            "keyString": "650140s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established the Hindu Dharma Sangrakshini Sabha in the year 1893 by : \n",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Dyanand Sarshawati  ",
            "optionD": "  Damodar and Balkrishana Chapekar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo Brothers- Damodar and Balkrishna Chapekar began the process of revolutionary activities in India. They formed the \u2018Hindu Dharma Sangrakshini Sabha\u2019 in 1893 and started celebrating the birthday of Shivaji and Ganesh Utsavs. ",
            "keyString": "650215s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bande Matram was a series of articles published in the year 1907 by :\n",
            "optionA": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionC": "  Domadar Chapekar ",
            "optionD": "  Balkrishana Chapekar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVande Matram was a series of articles published in the year 1907 by Sri Auronbindo Ghosh. ",
            "keyString": "650235s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was admired as tempestuous Hindu in 1893 in the World Parliament of Religious in Chicago ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Swami Dyanand Sarshawati ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Gautam Budha ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekanand ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda represented India and Hinduism at the Parliament of the World's Religions (1893). This was the first World's Parliament of Religions and it was held from 11 to 27 September 1893. ",
            "keyString": "650248s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who were associated with Indian league established in  1875  in Calcutta  (now Kolkata) ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Sisir Kumar Ghosh and Arvindo Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Kali Mohan Das and Arvindo Ghosh ",
            "optionC": "  Sisir Kumar Ghosh and Sambhu Charan Mukherjee ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSisir Kumar Ghosh and Sambhu Charan Mukherjee were associated with Indian league established in 1875 in Calcutta. ",
            "keyString": "650260s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which revolutionary wrote books Colour of Swadeshi and Revolutionary Life?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Sukhdev ",
            "optionC": "  Pandit Ram Prasad Bismil ",
            "optionD": "  Raj Guru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPandit Ram Prasad Bismil wrote books Colour of Swadeshi and Revolutionary Life. ",
            "keyString": "689130s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which revolutionary was associated with the foundation of the Punjab Navjivan Bharat Sabha in 1926?",
            "optionA": "  Rash Behari Bose ",
            "optionB": "  Amir Chand ",
            "optionC": "  Basant Kumar Biswas ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was founded by Bhagat Singh in March 1926 and was a more public face of the Hindustan Republican Association. The NBS comprised members from the Hindu, Muslim and Sikh communities and organised lectures, public meetings and protests. ",
            "keyString": "689163s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The novel \u2018Neel Darpan\u2019 depicting the harassment and oppression of Indigo farmers by the Britishers was written by:",
            "optionA": "  M M Malviya ",
            "optionB": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Dinabandhu Mitra ",
            "optionD": "  Sisir Kumar Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe novel \u2018Neel Darpan\u2019 depicting the harassment and oppression of Indigo farmers by the Britishers was written by Dinabandhu Mitra. ",
            "keyString": "689177s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who led the revolt in 1857 in Bihar and defeated the British Army near Aara?",
            "optionA": "  Bahadur Shah Jafar ",
            "optionB": "  Kunwar  Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Tatya Tope ",
            "optionD": "  Mangal Pandey ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKunwar Singh led the Indian Rebellion of 1857 in Bihar. He was nearly eighty and in failing health when he was called upon to take up arms. He gave a good fight and harried British forces for nearly a year and remained invincible until the end. He was an expert in the art of guerilla warfare. ",
            "keyString": "689189s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote famous thesis entitled \u2018South India in 1857: war of Independence\u2019:",
            "optionA": "  J K Hikki ",
            "optionB": "  K M Pannikar ",
            "optionC": "  M G Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  V.",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian War of Independence is an Indian nationalist history of the 1857 revolt by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar that was first published in 1909. ",
            "keyString": "689201s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded Satya Shodhak Samaj in 1873 ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Shri Bharat Kumar ",
            "optionB": "  Purushottam Das Tandon ",
            "optionC": "  Bankim Chandra Chattopashyay ",
            "optionD": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyashodhak Samaj (Truth-seekers' Society) is a social reform society founded by Jyotirao Phule in Pune, India, on 24 September 1873. ",
            "keyString": "729534s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first President of Indian National congress was :\n",
            "optionA": "  Sir Womesh Chunder Bonnerjee. ",
            "optionB": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionC": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  George Yule ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWomesh Chunder Bonnerjee (29 December 1844 \u2013 21 July 1906) was an Indian barrister and was the first president of Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "729566s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who conveyed to the Indians \u2013 \"I am with you wholeheartedly and in terms of culture I am one of you\u201d?\n",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Badruddin Tyabji ",
            "optionC": "  George Yule ",
            "optionD": "  Sir William Wedderburn ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant conveyed to the Indians \u2013 \"I am with you wholeheartedly and in terms of culture I am one of you\u201d.",
            "keyString": "729579s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurobindo Ghose, Barindra Kumar Ghose, B.P. Mitra, Abinash Bhattacharya and Bhupendranath Dutta were associated with the revolutionary organization :\n",
            "optionA": "  Anushilan Samiti (in Bengal). ",
            "optionB": "  Satya Shodhak Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal Society ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurobindo Ghose, Barindra Kumar Ghose, B.P. Mitra, Abinash Bhattacharya and Bhupendranath Dutta were associated with the revolutionary organization Anushilan Samiti (in Bengal). ",
            "keyString": "729592s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main centre of Gadar Movement of 1915 was :",
            "optionA": "  United States of America. ",
            "optionB": "  Japan ",
            "optionC": "  Australia ",
            "optionD": "  Singapore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1914, Kasi Ram Joshi a member of the party from Haryana, returned to India from America. On 15 March 1915 he was hanged by the colonial government. The Ghadar party commanded a loyal following the province of Punjab, but many of its most prominent activists were forced into exile to Canada and the United States. ",
            "keyString": "729604s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maulana qasim Nanautavi, Rashid Ahmad Gangohi, Sheikhul Hind Maulana- Mahmud-ul Hasan were the prominent figures who represented?",
            "optionA": "  Deoband Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Santhal Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Indigo Movement ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the Indian Rebellion of 1857, Darul Uloom Deoband learning centre was established on 21 May 1866 by Maulana Muhammad Qasim Nanautavi. The Deobandi Islamic movement originated in the Darul Uloom. ",
            "keyString": "771993s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the history of Indian National Movement Santhal Rebellion took place between :\n",
            "optionA": "  1845-47 ",
            "optionB": "  1849-50 ",
            "optionC": "  1855-56 ",
            "optionD": "  1866-67 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSanthal rebellion 1855-56. The Santhal rebellion predates 1857. It was a rebellion of Santhal people led by 4 Murmu Brothers named Sindhu, Kanhu , Chand and Bhairav, in modern Jharkhand (then Bengal Presidency) against the oppressive Zamindari system. The initially launched Guerilla warfare in the Jungles of Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "772083s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famine which killed nearly 8 lakh people during British rule as per the report furnished by the Femine Commissioon of 1660  had struck :",
            "optionA": "  Eastern India ",
            "optionB": "  Northern India ",
            "optionC": "  Southern India ",
            "optionD": "  Western India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famine which killed nearly 8 lakh people during British rule as per the report furnished by the Femine Commissioon of 1660had struck Western India. ",
            "keyString": "772114s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called the revolt of 1857 as a war between barbarism and civilization?",
            "optionA": "  V A Smith ",
            "optionB": "  T. R. Holmes ",
            "optionC": "  J K Hikki ",
            "optionD": "  Sir Ahmed Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tT. R. Holmes popularized the view that the Revolt of 1857 was a conflict between civilization and barbarism or a struggle between Oriental and Occidental civilization and culture.",
            "keyString": "772142s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the author of the book \u2018The Great Rebellion\u2019?\n",
            "optionA": "  Robert Knight ",
            "optionB": "  T N Das ",
            "optionC": "  Ashok Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  K M Pannikar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Author of the Great Rebellion is Ashok Mehta. The great rebellion was the story set in the year of 1857 when Indian freedom fighters fought for independence. ",
            "keyString": "772169s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The twenty-third Jaina teacher, Parsva, the immediate predecessor of Mahavira enjoined on his disciples four great vows. To these Mahavira adds which of the followings as the fifth vow?",
            "optionA": "  Abstention from stealing ",
            "optionB": "  Non-injury ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmacharya or continence ",
            "optionD": "  Non-attachment ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe twenty-third Jaina teacher, Parsva, the immediate predecessor of Mahavira enjoined on his disciples four great vows. To these Mahavira adds theBrahmacharya or continence as the fifth vow. ",
            "keyString": "810204s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Turko-Afghan rule in India lasted for about",
            "optionA": "  two centuries ",
            "optionB": "  three centuries ",
            "optionC": "  four centuries ",
            "optionD": "  a little over one century ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTurko Afghan rule in India lasted for about 3 centuries as they were there in the time of Rana Pratap also and the Turkish king Gaznavi invaded Delhi long before that. ",
            "keyString": "810237s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not included in Mughal paintings? ",
            "optionA": "  Portraits ",
            "optionB": "  Islamic themes ",
            "optionC": "  Flowers and plants ",
            "optionD": "  Hunting scenes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe painting which is not included in the Mughal paintings is the Islamic Themes. Mughal paintings\u00a0are a particular style of South Asian painting. These paintings were evolved during the rule of Mughal Emperors in India and revolved around themes like battles, legendary stories, hunting scenes, wildlife, royal life, mythology, etc. ",
            "keyString": "810251s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Against which Mughal Emperor was a FATWA issued from Jaunpur? ",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar was the Mughal Emperor against whom the Fatwa was issued from Jaunpur. ",
            "keyString": "810263s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who gave the slogan DO OR DIE during the quit India movement in 1942?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1942, in a fiery speech in Mumbai, Mahatma Gandhi gave a 'do or die' call to the people of India in a final push to make the British quit. ",
            "keyString": "810275s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded Atmiya Sabha in 1815?",
            "optionA": "  Brahma Datt ",
            "optionB": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAtmiya Sabha was a philosophical discussion circle in India. The association was started by Ram Mohan Roy in 1815 in Kolkata (then Calcutta). They used to conduct debate and discussion sessions on philosophical topics, and also used to promote free and collective thinking and social reform. ",
            "keyString": "887935s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote in 1900 to the Secretary of state for India-\u2018It is my firm belief that the congress is staggering towards its downfall and it is my great desire that during my stay in India I should help in its peaceful demise?\"",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Minto ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon wrote in 1900 to the Secretary of state for India-\u2018It is my firm belief that the congress is staggering towards its downfall and it is my great desire that during my stay in India I should help in its peaceful demise.\" ",
            "keyString": "887968s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak popularly known as Lokamanya Tilak was born in 1856 at",
            "optionA": "  Ratnagiri ",
            "optionB": "  Pune ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak was born in a Marathi Chitpavan Brahmin family in Ratnagiri as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, in the headquarters of the eponymous district of present-day Maharashtra (then British India) on 23 July 1856. ",
            "keyString": "887983s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An English weekly called \u2018New India\u2019 was started by;",
            "optionA": "  K M Pannikar ",
            "optionB": "  Devendra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew India was an early 20th century daily newspaper published in India by the Annie Besant, to highlight issues related to the Indian freedom struggle. ",
            "keyString": "887995s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bang Darshan was the main newspaper of",
            "optionA": "  Sisir Kumar Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Birendra Nath Chatterjee ",
            "optionC": "  Pini Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBangadarshan was a Bengali literary magazine, founded by Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay in 1872, and resuscitated in 1901 under the editorship of Rabindranath Tagore. The magazine had a defining influence on the emergence of a Bengali identity and the genesis of nationalism in Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "888007s53m53h10d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}